<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Soveraign omnipotency the saint's security in evil days Discoursed and concluded from Rom. IV. xvii, xviii.</title>
            <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7032A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897630</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137265</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137265)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2510:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Soveraign omnipotency the saint's security in evil days Discoursed and concluded from Rom. IV. xvii, xviii.</title>
                  <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 101, [3], 95 [i.e. 65], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Benj. Alsop, at the Angel and Bible in the Poultrey; and are to be sold by James Cowsey, bookseller in Exeter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a separate dated title page: The justice of God asserted, in seeming contrariants providences; with separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>P. 65 misnumbered "95".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soveraign Omnipotency</hi> The SAINT's SECURITY IN Evil Days. Diſcourſed and Concluded From <hi>Rom.</hi> IV. xvii, xviii.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>WILLIAM CROMPTON.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Exod. 14.13.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Stand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>2 Chron. 20.12.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O our God, wilt Thou not judge them? for we have no might againſt this great Company that cometh againſt us, neither know we what to do, but our Eyes are upon thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Alſop,</hi> at the Angel and Bible in the <hi>Poultrey;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>James Cowſey,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Exeter.</hi> 1682.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:2"/>
                  <p>Digniſsimo, Amiciſsimoque Affini noſtro, <hi>GEORGIO YONG,</hi> Creditonenſium, In Agro <hi>Devonienſi</hi> Armigero: Nec-non <hi>GEORGIO LAPTHORN, Plymidenſium,</hi> Mercatori Celeberrimo: Nomine Virtutis non mihi ſolum noto: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>triſque Sacrarum Literarum Patronis Candidiſſimis. Conciones ſequentes, tum Potentiae Divinae ſumme efficacis, aeque ac Juſtitiae illius omnimodo incontaminabilis, Doctrinans Dilucidantes: <hi>D. D. D.</hi> Fauſtaque iiſdem omnia, non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus calido voto, quam ipſimet, in hoc ſcripto <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> comprecatur;</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Guliel. Crompton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137265:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Soveraign Omnipotency</hi> THE SAINTS SECURITY In Evil Days.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>ROM. iv. 17, 18.</bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Even God who quickneth the dead, and calleth thoſe things that are not, as though they were.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>THis part of the Chapter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains an Illuſtrious Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Renowned <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and that Faith whereby he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Promiſe to <hi>be the Father of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations;</hi> and is deſcribed three ways, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:137265:4"/>
                     <p n="1">1. By the nature of it, which he diſcovers to be <hi>ſincere;</hi> not only out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly profeſt, (though that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary) but inwardly rooted. It was Faith <hi>before God,</hi> and found Acceſs into the Divine Preſence.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By the <hi>extent</hi> of the Relation between <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Faithful; and ſo, it is defined to be <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> as God is Father of all, <hi>Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> without diſtinction of Nation, Sex and Condition. <hi>Spiritual,</hi> before him whom he believed; not <hi>Carnal,</hi> nor apprehended by men without a Revelation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>The Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs to him, neither can he know them, for they are Spiritually diſcern'd.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. From the <hi>ground</hi> of both, which is the Soveraignty and Almighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God; ſet forth by two things, <hi>viz. Quickning the Dead, and call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ng things that are not as though they were.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This ſupported <hi>Ahrahams</hi> Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſeeming Impoſſibilities; and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ended ſubject of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. In the Proſecution of which, I ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll labour firſt to break the Shell, by expl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ining the words, as they ſh ll
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137265:4"/> fall under conſideration, and then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you the Kernel contained in it; Firſt I ſhall endeavour to unlock the Cabinet and then ſhew you the rich Jewels laid up in it; which you will find to be of great worth and uſe in theſe Cloudy days, wherein the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence hath caſt us.</p>
                     <p>For the former Branch; 1. <hi>Gods quickning the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Short Sentence and diverſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by divers Divines. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is hereby meant, preſent in Soul, future of Body; with ſome ſpecial Limitation to <hi>Abraham.</hi> As,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. A raiſing of ſuch a <hi>Seed</hi> out of his <hi>dead</hi> Body. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19. <hi>And being not weak in Faith, he conſidered not his own Body now dead, when he was about an hundred years old, neither yet the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of</hi> Sarahs <hi>Womb.</hi> i. e. Deſtitute of all natural power to conceive and quicken. Yet <hi>Abraham</hi> could ſet his Seal to it, by Faith, as being within the Limits of Gods power.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. A recovering of that Seed alive from the dead, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that God was able to raiſe him up, even from the Dead, from whence alſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137265:5"/> he received him in a Figure;</hi> which to nature and humane apprehenſion was impoſſible. Yet this <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, becauſe of the Lords <hi>All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. A reviving of the Body out of the Duſt, at the laſt <hi>Day:</hi> which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> believed the Lord was able, and would certainly do it.</p>
                     <p>The whole commends two things to our Learning.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, <hi>To quicken the Dead, is the Lords priviledge, an effect of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>That this Divine Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould be to us a Ground of Fai h.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the former. See it promiſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> chap. 26. ver. 19. <hi>Thy Dead Men ſhall Live, together with my Dead Body ſhall they Ariſe.</hi> To be underſtood either in a Phyſical or Moral Senſe; with the Concurrent Conſent of the Ancient and Learned Modern Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; who obſerve, that there is nothing more uſual for the Church, and Holy Men therein, to Support their Hearts above all Incumbent Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and to Secure themſelves of the Comfort of promiſed Deliverance, notwithſtanding all the ſeeming Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137265:5"/> thereof, by the General Doctrine of the Reſurrection. And ſo, <hi>John</hi> 5,21,28. <hi>The Father raiſeth up the Dead and Quickneth them, even ſo the Son quickneth whom he will.</hi> On which Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ount Chriſt is declared to <hi>be the Son of God, by the Reſurrection from the Dead; R m.</hi> 1.4. <hi>First,</hi> Raiſing others; as he did the <hi>Rulers Daughter,</hi> to the Aſtoniſhment of all Beholders preſent at her Funeral; and the <hi>Widow</hi>'s Son of <hi>Naim,</hi> who was carried without the City to his Grave; Chriſt ſtops the ſad Train, and Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Life to the Young Man, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more Dear than Life to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And the more Signally to Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over Death, he Purſued it to its Fort, the Obſcurity of the Grave. <hi>Lazarus</hi> was buried for four Daies, his Carkaſs was Corrupt, but Chriſt called him from the Bottom of his Tomb with that Powerful Voice that Created the World; The Dead An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers and comes forth to the Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all that ſaw the Glory of God, ſo Clearly Manifeſted. In all, he Teſtified his Godhead, and the Truth of his Calling and Doctrine. Thus he raiſed <hi>Moſes and Elias,</hi> and made
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137265:6"/> them known to his Diſciples by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Revelation, to Evince his Doctrine not to be new, but the ſame in Subſtance with that Record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Law and the Prophets;</hi> both being repreſented by <hi>Moſes and Elias;</hi> who though they were raiſed before him, yet it was not without him, but by the <hi>Fellowſhip of his Reſurrection:</hi> As, though Light Riſeth before the Sun, yet it Riſeth not but by the Sun; and the Mace goeth before the Magiſtrate, but it doth ſo only to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon him.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, Raiſing himſelf. <hi>John</hi> 10,18. <hi>I have laid down my Life, that I might take it again, no Man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of my ſelf; I have Power to lay it down, and I have Power to Raiſe it up again.</hi> Here is a glorious Manifeſtation of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the Tomb could not Confine him, nor the Grave-Stone ſtay him; But throwing off thoſe Clogs, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his <hi>Withs,</hi> he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a while to his Beloved Ones, and ſo took his Joyous Aſcent to the Right hand of the Father. As <hi>Love</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id Chriſt in the Grave, ſo <hi>Power</hi> Raiſed him from the Grave. <hi>Love</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:137265:6"/> Rockt him a Sleep, and <hi>Power</hi> Awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him again. He broke through all Bars, Beat down all Oppoſition, and Sprang forth of his yeilding Duſt, as a Triumphant Conqueror over Death and Devils.</p>
                     <p>If it be objected, <hi>That Chriſt roſe from the Dead by the Glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that the Father raiſed him?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is eaſily anſwered; This was not by way of ſupplement, to make up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defect of power in Chriſt, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by way of conſent, to Chriſts own Power and Action; that ſo men might Honour the Son and the Father. <hi>John.</hi> 5.19,26. Or elſe, <hi>by the Glory of the Father,</hi> we may underſtand that Glorious Power which the Father gave unto the Son in the Fleſh, to have life from himſelf; becauſe that holy Spirit which immediatly quickned him, was both his and the Fathers, and ſo the Action was common to both. Thus like the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>enix,</hi> he goeth out of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pulcher in the day of his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, al lighted and environ'd with Flames of Triumphant Glory.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Aſſuring others, by his lights and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>en or, that they ſhall riſe again. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. He is called <hi>the firſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137265:7"/> Fruits of them that Sleep.</hi> The Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Reſurrection of our Lord, is the Root and Hope of ours; with this he ſweetens the acerbities of our preſent life, and repleniſheth Hearts with the Antipaſt of their Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; for, he aroſe not barely in a Perſonal, but Publick Capacity; and though it were a Damnable Hereſy of <hi>Hymeneus,</hi> to ſay, <hi>That the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was paſt already;</hi> Yet it is a truth to ſay, that it is begun. He firſt, and <hi>we at his coming,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25. By what is paſt in the head, we are aſſured of what is expected in his Members; for, his Reſurrection is a Pledge and Earneſt of theirs. He having paid our Debt, Death cannot detain us in Priſon for it. Yea, it is a beginning of ours, as before is noted; he being raiſed who is the Head, the Body muſt alſo follow. If the Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſprung out of the Duſt, the Younger Brethren ſhall not ſtay there. The Vine-Plant being in Heaven, there the Branches muſt receive their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Flouriſh.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Object. 1.</label> Is it not ſaid, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.2. <hi>By man came the Reſurrection of the Dead?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:137265:7"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>A.</label> It is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſuch a man as is God alſo; from whoſe Will this large Soul of Nature had its motion, and who therein commandeth ſo univerſally, as he ſeems to hold the Heaven and Elements under here, to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Wonders; it is he that lighted Stars at his Birth, and Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Ancient Sun at his Death, and walked on the waters as on a Pavement of Marble. It is he, that cauſeth the <hi>Earth to caſt out her Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Object. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>Have not men done it?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſwer.</label> 1. Stories of Men Raiſed by Men, are either Lies and Illuſions, as the Pythoniſt of <hi>Endor</hi> raiſed the Devil in <hi>Samuels</hi> Shape; and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maintain many Idle Stories of Dead men Raiſed, to Walk and Live after Death. Otherwayes, Dead Men neither walk nor appear in Body or Soul, after Death. Or, if there are any ſuch, They are extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Permiſſions, for Secret Ends, only known to him that Permits them.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Prophets and Apoſtles have done it, but in the Quality of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. So <hi>Eliſha</hi> raiſed the <hi>Shunamites</hi> Son, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4.34. And <hi>Peter</hi> raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137265:8"/> 
                        <hi>Dorcas, Acts</hi> 9.40. But not by their own Power. It only belongs to Chriſt to do this work, with an <hi>Original Power,</hi> which hath its Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in his Boſom; with an <hi>Abſolute Command,</hi> which receives no Modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in all Nature; with a <hi>Simple Will,</hi> which needs no other Inſtrument. It was by Divine Influence and Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in thoſe Prophets and Apoſtles, to confirm their Doctrine, and to draw the Church ſooner to believe.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It is the Divine Nature that is the Fountain of Life; he gives, takes, reſtores, to whom, when, and how he pleaſeth. As it is with the Sea for water and the Sun for light, in the former, all the waters are gathered together into an Ocean, where they grow into ſwelling heaps, and are the ſource of all the Streams that refreſh the Earth; and in the latter, that great Luminarie is the Veſſel, wherein the Lord hath gathered all light, which before was ſattered in the Heavens, but is now united in that bright Lamp, which, running like a fiery Chariot, might rule the day, and illuſtrate the earth, making it fruitful. Thus it is with the Deity for life, <hi>John</hi> 6.63.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137265:8"/> 
                        <hi>The Spirit quickneth, the Fleſh profiteth nothing; The words that I ſpeak unto you are Spirit and Life.</hi> And by this power <hi>he quickneth the Dead.</hi> So that it's clear, the work is his, who is Lord of nature, and holds the Keys of life and death in his own hands. His light only can diſpel the darkneſs, and his voice only can break the ſilence of the Grave.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Doctrine comes now to hand, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Doct. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>That this Divine Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould be to us a ground of Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gen. 17.1. <hi>I am God all-ſufficient, walk before me,</hi> &amp;c. Walk before me who am <hi>all-ſufficient,</hi> ſelf-ſufficient, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, Univerſal Good; the Pillar of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith. And the Apoſtle ſpeaks by way of wonder that any ſhould not believe it, <hi>Acts.</hi> 26.8. <hi>Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with you, That God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</hi> Therefore it is that the Sacred Scripture doth frequently mind us of his power, to help our incredulitie; <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.19. <hi>God is not as man, that he ſhould lie, nor the Son of man, that he ſhould repent; hath he ſaid it, and ſhall he not do it? or hath he ſpoken, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137265:9"/> ſhall he not make it good?</hi> And again, <hi>Is there any thing too hard for God?</hi> So, <hi>Math.</hi> 19.27. <hi>With God all things are poſſible.</hi> A main prop to an humble Suppliant, That ſeeing his own vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Divine Excellencies, which are warming and enlightning, cryeth out, <hi>Lord if thou wilt, thou canſt make me clean,</hi> as it is recorded, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. This is the Rock, on which the weak Anchor of a Chriſtians Faith may firmly fix. You know <hi>Sampſons</hi> Riddle; <hi>Out of the Eater cometh forth Sweet.</hi> The reaſon why Chriſtians ſhould conſider the power of God; out of this ſtrong comes forth ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</p>
                     <p>In the application hereof may be found,</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1.</label> Matter of <hi>Correction,</hi> and that of two ſorts:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> of ſuch that make it too hard; denying the Reſurrection in <hi>opinion.</hi> As Pearls are diſſolved in Vinegar, ſo is Truth in hearts made bitter with Corruption. Thus we find many wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and irregular Spirits, who having renounced the bleſſings of the other life, againſt the voice of nature in the order of the World, wherein we have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137265:9"/> the New Birth of Stars, days, Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Plants and Birds, who make a perpetual Image of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> in the World; nay, againſt the touch of God, and impreſſions of verity on the very Gentiles, who have profeſſed the happineſs of the Soul in the other life and the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> even on their Tombs, to deny the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> So the <hi>Saduces</hi> of old, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.8. <hi>Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 18. which you may eaſily perceive, is not only to crack the eye of a reaſonable judgment, but alſo to pull out the eye of Faith, all pure and caeleſtial as it is.</p>
                     <p>Or, in <hi>practice;</hi> Let us eat and <hi>drink for to morrow we ſhall die,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. Of thoſe, I mean, who drown their Souls in their Bodies and would have no time to live longer, than they have to ſin, and when there is an end of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wiſh there would be an end of living. And well it would be for them, if living like Beaſts, they might be annihilated like Beaſts. Thus men do err, not knowing the power of God. That God, who out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Created all things, can certainly reduce many things into one. When the Body is gone into a thouſand ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137265:10"/> he can eaſily make an abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and bring that Body together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; as a Chymiſt, out of ſeveral Metals mingled together can abſtract one from the other, the Silver from the Gold, and the Alchimy from the Silver, and reduce every Metal to its own kind. Thus ſhould we much more believe of God, that he is able to extract and reinveſt every Soul with its own Body, though they are ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and confounded with many other Subſtances.</p>
                     <p>The Perſecutors of the Primitive Chriſtians burnt their Bodies into Aſhes and caſt them into the River, and all, <hi>ad tollendam ſpem Reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis;</hi> but all in vain, for even they alſo ſhall ariſe to a better Reſurrection; for, at the Shrill Voice of the laſt Trumpet, the greateſt Jaylors ſhall ſurrrender up all their Priſoners; all the ſcatter'd Duſt of <hi>Adams</hi> Seed ſhall ride upon Windy Wings, till it meet together in a collected Body. All the Creatures in the world, that have made their Meat of mans fleſh, ſhall finde that they have eaten Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels too hard for the digeſtion of their weak Stomach, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19. <hi>The earth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137265:10"/> ſhall caſt forth her Dead,</hi> as a woman doth an untimely Birth; the <hi>Grave</hi> ſhall be in travel with the Dead, and ſhall be delivered of them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Such as make this work too eaſie, ſaying they can quicken them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; againſt all ſenſe and common reaſon. It is to maintain a propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ridiculous to all humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Can any thing make it ſelf? neither can any reaſonable Creature raiſe it ſelf to an higher rank of being than it is. A Stone cannot make it ſelf a Tree, to have growth and life; nor can a Tree make it ſelf a Beaſt, to have ſenſe, nor a Beaſt make it ſelf a man to have Reaſon, nor a Rational man make himſelf a Saint. Or elſe, aſcribe it to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe of Nature, depriving the Lord of his Royal Prerogative.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</label> Here is matter offered of ſtrong conſolation and encouragement to the holy ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> you believe in him who can quicken the dead. For your ſakes, let me take leave, a little to open this Cabinet, that you may view the excellency of this powerful God in whom you believe; and be ſure the proſpect will be very pleaſing.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:137265:11"/>
                     <p>Death, and ſo the Dead, may be conſidered three ways:</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Politice;</hi> There is a Death of Kingdomes and States; as there is a riſing and flouriſhing, ſo there is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying and dying, they ſpring, flouriſh and dye; the goodlieſt, and ſtatelieſt Politick Bodies that ever the earth bore, though animated with the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit of the moſt profound Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſtrengthned with the reſolution and valour of the moſt Unconquer'd, ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Eagles eyes, of largeſt depths, and comprehenſions of States and Crowns, adorned with never ſo many proſperities, and Triumphs; yet like the natural Body of a man, they have their revolutions and decays. Moſt apparent, in the ruines of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, once a glorious Body; and the once ſplendor of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Monarchie, and the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, which ſprang from the moſt contemptible beginning; with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> State, which once appear'd like a Comet, threatning deſtruction an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> giving Laws to all the Nations round about her. The Beams and Raſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ors of a State may be ſo link<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> together, ſo tenton'd and ſet into one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137265:11"/> another, as might embolden a bare Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litician to determine it an indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſtitution: But God under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines all with the Breath of his Mouth. And Politicians have obſerved, that the longeſt liv'd State on Earth, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers great alterations and Periods within the compaſs of four or five hundred years.</p>
                     <p>This decay is, 1. In matters <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical,</hi> concerning Religion. As the Church prays, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 80.18. <hi>Quicken us, we call upon thee.</hi> And the power of Chriſt Shines marvellouſly in the great Empire of his Church, which the Father hath put into his hands, to build, raiſe and cement with his Blood, illuminate with his Light, and nouriſh with his Body. To confirm which, the Hiſtorian hath obſerv'd, how the Doctrine of the <hi>Albigenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, notwithſtanding all enemies; and he hids all the Privy Counſellours of Nature, who can tell where the Swallows lie all the Winter, and how at the Spring they have a Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from their ſeeming deadneſs; Let them, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h he, alſo inform u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, in what inviſible Sanctuary, this Doctrine did lurk, in ſpice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll oppoſition and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137265:12"/> and how it reviv'd out of its Aſhes, at the coming of <hi>Luther.</hi> And withal he obſerves, that in thoſe parts of <hi>France,</hi> where the <hi>Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> were moſt cruelly handled, now the Proteſtants (the Heirs of moſt of their Tenents) moſt Flouriſh.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In matters <hi>Civil,</hi> touching the Law and matter of Government; as the Lord promiſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19. <hi>Thy Dead Body ſhall live,</hi> &amp;c. Before, they complained of very hard labour, and that they brought forth nothing but Wind; now, <hi>thy Dead Body ſhall Live.</hi> Which ſome refer to the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſh Captivity,</hi> wherein they were as <hi>Dead Bones</hi> in the Grave, without any Strength, Wiſdom, or viſible hope of being delivered; yet though they ſeemed ſo very much decayed, as if they were quite withered and Conſumed with Calamity and Death, he promiſed to raiſe them again, and Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h them with Beauty and Glory Thus the <hi>Lord quickens the Dead.</hi> If he burn his Phenix, out of the very Aſhes he will raiſe another.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Phyſice;</hi> And that is the Death of the Body, of which we have ſpoken already. <hi>The E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rth ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll caſt forth her
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137265:12"/> Dead.</hi> This is eaſie to God, to whom Miracles are as eaſie as natural ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. A Miracle being nothing elſe but a new Creation.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Ethice;</hi> Which is the Death of the Soul; Two fold, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary; either by the abſence of Grace or Divine Diſcretion; when Man is indeed Dead, or as a dead thing, in his own apprehenſion, the <hi>Lord quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. You who were Dead he quickneth.</hi> Man is Impotent and weak, like a dead Member in the Body, he is in himſelf <hi>without Strength:</hi> And as the Organs can make no ſound, unleſs Breath be cauſed to enter into them, ſo neither can a dead Soul make any Harmony, till God breathe into it, by his Bleſſed Spirit. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Eternal, when the perſon is actually cut off from all hope, and irrecoverably ſhut up in the eternal Abyſs. So, the Lord doth not, he will not quicken, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26. There is a great Gulf, a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Wall between Hell and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, ſo that they who paſs from earth to Hell cannot return, <hi>&amp;c. Tali pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatione non Datur Progreſſus;</hi> That Gulf being fixed by the immutable and immoveable Decree of God.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:137265:13"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>Q.</label> 
                        <hi>How doth the Lord quicken the Dead?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> 1. By ordering all that falls out in the World, for the good of his People, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.12,13. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, O my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I will open your Graves, and cauſe you to come ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of your Graves, and bring you into the Land of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>and ye ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I have opened your Graves, O my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ught you up out of your Graves.</hi> When things were brought to a dead L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen he puts to his hand, his Strength is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de known; and when the danger is moſt felt, then his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Arm is moſt welcome. When the Daughter of the Ruler of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue was dead, then Ch iſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red moſt advantagiouſl, <hi>Mark</hi> 5. That was the word he wait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d for, and longed to hear. As <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xander</hi> the Great ſolaced himſelf with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Peril in <hi>Indi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Tand m par Animo meo periculum video;</hi> So fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it with our abſolute Monarch of the World, it is Joy to his heart to protract his time, till he ſee the height and maturity of danger, that ſo he may get the more honour. While things are but dying, there is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137265:13"/> hope in nature, and in reſpect of us; but when they are quite <hi>dead,</hi> there is hope, if we look up to God, and believe him <hi>who quickneth the Dead.</hi> We need not meddle with the great Current of his Counſels; his Power in the object of our Faith. He can make light in the midſt of duskie Nights, and Havens in the moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn Shipwrack; and if we were with him in the Shadow of Death, what ſhould we fear in the Arms of Life?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By infuſing Grace and working Life. The Method or order he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> to kill by the Law, and then to quicken by the Goſpel. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he Wounds, and <hi>then</hi> Heals; He uſeth Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, but ſuch as are dipt in Balm. And ſo the Lord quickens daily, and often wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ks a Miracle; and this in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r upon his Son <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en; and thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re by degrees drawn by Chriſt to him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>lf, and united to him b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Life Commu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> d to them. As th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> in the heart, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>lf, and ſends fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>y united part, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h and the whole there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ontin i y, <hi>John</hi> 5.25. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, The Hour is coming and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137265:14"/> now is, when the Dead ſhall hear the Voice of the Son of God, they ſhall hear and Live.</hi> John 14. and 19. <hi>Becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. By returning every Body his own Spirit. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.5. <hi>I will cauſe Breath to enter into you, and ye ſhall live.</hi> The ſame Body that dies ſhall riſe again. According to the hope of bleſſed Souls, who after the Viſion of God, do yet hope for the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Bodies, to which they moſt ardently wiſh to be reunited. As they, who are repreſented under the Altar, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. and at the Tribunal of Juſtice, ask vengeance of their Blood, are inſtantly Cloathed with <hi>White Garments,</hi> in Token of that bright Fleſh, which is to be joyned to their Immortal Spirits. However ſome have conceived, that the Soul ſhall be cloathed with a new Body; which if it ſhould be granted, what would the Reſurrection be, but a new Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aton?</p>
                     <p>This Doctrine of the Reſurrection, is ſuch, that it is too deep for Reaſon to wade, you muſt let Faith ſwim. It is infinitely above Reaſon to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and we have ſcarce Faith enough
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137265:14"/> to believe it. Have an Eye to Chriſt, reſt on the Almighty Power. And ſo let me add in the next place.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. An Uſe of <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and that in two things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>First,</hi> Never to <hi>diſpair,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Not of the State, ſhould that be as low as <hi>Iſrael, Ezek.</hi> 37.11,12. <hi>Son of Man, thoſe Bones are the Houſe of Iſrael, behold, they ſay our ſtrength is dryed, and our hope is loſt; we are cut off for our parts; Therefore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy and ſay unto them, Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, O my people, I will open your Graves, and cauſe you to come up out of your Graves, and bring you into the Land of</hi> Iſrael. Though things ſeem to Humane Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, helpleſs and hopeleſs, look up to the Supream Power, who can, beyond all our thoughts, make thoſe who dwell in the Duſt, to awake and Sing. This Doctrine ſpeaks good news in that reſpect. There is <hi>Balm in Gile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad,</hi> and a Phyſician to heal, and this Phyſician yet dwelleth in our Hemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phere, with Healing under his Wings. Deſpair not, though it be brought ſo low as the Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 21.5. <hi>who had no Meat:</hi> This Lord can turn
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:137265:15"/> Stones into Bread. Let us all pray, Lord increaſe our Faith!</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Deſpair not of others, who are dead, and have a long time lain in the Grave of Sin. Only ſpeak to and for them; as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.9. <hi>Come from the four Winds, O Breath, and breathe upon theſe Slain, that they may Live.</hi> You that have Sick, Dying, yea, Dead Relations, Children, Servants, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Let your Bowels yearn over them; Lift up a Prayer for them; the Prayer of Faith may Heal the Sick, and Save a Dead Soul. No better Phyſick to be given at a Dead Lift, in the moſt deſperate Caſe, than Prayer. All you that have felt the Diſeaſe of Sin, and the Powerful Mercy of Chriſt, learn to pity others, and hope for their Healing and Quickning. He can turn noiſom Dunghils into Mines of Gold, Brands of Hell into Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Stars in his Firmament.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Deſpair not of your ſelves; though you have no Spiritual Life, but are all over like a Dead Carkaſs; yet wait at the gate of this great Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician; there may be a <hi>Time of Love</hi> come, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.6,8. He works at all hours. You may Reap if you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137265:15"/> Faint not. <hi>Deus veſter eſt Deus Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vificus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> be Inſtructed, to prepare dayly for the generall Reſurrection, for the coming of the great day of God, wherein he may give you new Bodies, Immortal, Agile, Incorupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Priviledged with Favours, and Gilded with the Bright Splendours of the Body of Chriſt Jeſus. You are haſting towards that Eternal Eſtate every day. Forſake, Forſake the Love of theſe ſleight Cottages, thoſe poor Ant-hills, which Enthral ſo many Spirits, deveſted of thoſe Divine Seeds which bud under Generous and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Breaſts.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Uſe the means, and look through them to Chriſt; ſtill ſaying, I have a Dead Heart, O Lord, ſome quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Grace! Chriſt is not of more Power then Sympathy. <hi>You hath he quickned, who were Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Be thankful for Spiritual Life, in Poſſeſſion or Expectation. In this God hath done more for you, than if he had made you Princes of the Earth. In this, he hath done more for you, than if he had made you Angels. O be thankful! God in Quickning you,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:137265:16"/> hath done more for you, than if he had given you the World. Let your Hearts and Mouths be filled with Praiſes. It is a Mercy calls for your higheſt Praiſes in the Days of Eternity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>THe <hi>Second</hi> Branch of the Text which Illuſtrates the Omnipotent Soveraignty of Chriſt, comes next to be Conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calling things that are not, as though they were.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Effect or peculiar Property of the Deity, whereby God (with ſpecial Reference to Chriſt the Son, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m he believing was juſtified) is deſcribed.</p>
                     <p>The words are few, the Sentence ſhort, and hard to be underſtood: not how it is a ground of Faith; that eaſily follows; but how <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſhould be in the Divine Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, how the God of Truth ſhould Congruouſly and truely call things that are not, as though they were; this is difficult to conceive.</p>
                     <p>For the Clearing and Opening of it, to the weak Capacity of man, ſome have and may, provided it be done with Reverence, Sobriety, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:137265:16"/> Reference to the Scripture chiefly (for we cannot ſpeak of God, but as he hath ſpoken of himſelf) take Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to diſcourſe,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Of the Infinite Eſſence, Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending and Repreſenting all that ever ſhould have being, to the Divine Underſtanding.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Of the Infinite Preſence, and drawing together the whole Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time, as if preſent, not Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily but really, and Coexiſting with all time. <hi>I am that I am; i. e.</hi> The Abſolute Being, the Independent and firſt Original of all Eſſences; <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But while they have gone about in their own words to bring this Infinite Myſtery under mans finite Capacity, they have left it more Obſcure. I conceive it ſafer to be Contented with <hi>Scripture</hi> Phraſes, not as Moulded this or that way by humane Reaſon, but as they lye in the Text, <hi>viz. in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalibus,</hi> Large and General Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and not deſcend to curious Particulars; rather falling under an awful Adoration and Beleif, than an exact Extrance on any ſuch Subject, beyond what we may be aſſured is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:137265:17"/> This is to be wiſe to <hi>Sobriety:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eſpecially, Conſidering,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Our great Apoſtles Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. <hi>O the Depth of the Riches of the Wiſdom of God!</hi> where obſerve a Difference between Wiſdom and Knowledg. Knowledg is of things to come, though Inconvenient and Diſallowed; Wiſdom of things convenient and approved. As the excellent Dr. <hi>Twiſs, (Contr. Jackson)</hi> hath noted. And alſo his Impoſed Silence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. <hi>His unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able words, not Lawful for any to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It is not for you to know — Acts</hi> 1.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> The raſh and preſumptuous Adventure of ſome School-Divines, who, affecting Novelty and Obſcurity, deliver things hard to be underſtood (if not Impoſſible to be ſo) about the Divine Attributes, thoſe ſcorching and Peircing Beams, that others may fear to hear or read. Such curious Pries there have been into this Ark and Cabinet of Gods Secrets, not meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by the line of Humane Reaſon, or faſhionable by the Plummet of any Created Underſtanding. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould ſtill cry out, with that great Doctor of the Gentiles, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>!</p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:137265:17"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſidering how difficult a Paſſage it is; Nature helps little, and God hath ſpoken little of himſelf. How dangerous is it to Err? <hi>Homo ſum non Intelligo ſecreta Dei; Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare non Audeo; hoc ipſum Temerita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis genus eſt:</hi> ſaith <hi>Salvian, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Guber. Dei.</hi> And it was a grave and ſerious Speech of <hi>Seneca,</hi> worthy the Conſideration of the greateſt Divines, <hi>Nunquam nos Verecundiores eſſe debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quam de Deo Agitur.</hi> It ſhould not ſeem ſtrange, if ſtrucken with thoſe Rayes which dazle the Eyes of Seraphins, we yeild to his Greatneſs, and diſcourſe in the Secret Myſteries of the Scripture, with great Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and take heed that neither our Thoughts nor Tongues proceed any further, than the Bounds of Gods word do extend. We ſhould be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be Ignorant, where our great Maſter would not let us know. And, <hi>Neſcire velle quae Magiſter maximus nos ſcire non vult, Erudita Inſcitia eſt:</hi> as <hi>Scaliger</hi> hath expreſſed it. To all which I ſhall add that weighty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Renowned <hi>Calvin,</hi> who, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Inſtit: cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. Speaks to this Effect, How may the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:137265:18"/> Mind define the Immeaſurable Eſſence of God unſeen? and therefore with <hi>Moulin, Haec Perobſcura ſunt, et iimide et Religioſe Tranctanda.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ſhall therefore in handling this Text before us, do, as Men uſe to do in great Rivers or deep Waters, keep cloſe to the ſhoar, and Labour to have firm ground to walk by, both in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining and after in concluding thoſe plain Truths thence ariſing, moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for us.</p>
                     <p>For Explication, we may take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of three things.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The <hi>Subject,</hi> implyed, <hi>He;</hi> the Meſſiah, the Mediator. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was he that appeared to <hi>Abraham; Chriſt</hi> it was in whom he believed. He gave being to things that had no beings in the Creation. He blew the Univerſe into an Exiſtency by the Breath of his Mouth, and by his <hi>Fiat</hi> reared the Heaven and Earth with all therein; and he preſerveth them in being, and Reſtoreth them in and by the Reſurrection. An Invincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Chriſts Divinity againſt the <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Servetians,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enemies, who will not that Chriſt ſhould Reign over them, and will not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:137265:18"/> Honour him with any perſonal Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, till he was born into the world of the <hi>Virgin-Mary;</hi> they not being able to bear ſo Reſplendent a Light, have endeavour'd to obſcure it by the Fumes of their Brains.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The <hi>Work, Call.</hi> Taken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially three wayes in the Holy Scriptures: And ſo</p>
                     <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. <hi>I the Lord have called them in Righteouſneſs. Chap.</hi> 43.1. <hi>Fear not O Jacob, I have Redeemed thee, I have called thee by my Name,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavit,</hi> is uſed in both Texts. And ſo in the 147 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>He telleth the Number of the Stars, he calleth them all by Name.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this, either of things in <hi>Act,</hi> that have been or ſhall be; called <hi>Scientiam Purae Viſionis;</hi> or of things <hi>Poſſible;</hi> Called <hi>Scientiam pro Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>licis Intelligentiae,</hi> ſo far as they are knowable.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is taken for the <hi>Power</hi> of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alling: <hi>i. e.</hi> Cauſing not only things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat have no actual Exiſtence, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear as being; but giving them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng in time. So, in the Creation he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alled for Light, <hi>Fiat,</hi> and there was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:137265:19"/> Light; and ſo of other things; he calleth them into being, by his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Divine manner of working, which the Scripture calleth Creation, bringing them from <hi>not being</hi> to a <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> producing the matter of which they conſiſt, preparing and ſitting it, as now it is, Inveſting it with all thoſe Forms and Admirable Qualities, or which all the Motions of their Nature do depend. And elſe-where, it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſaid, <hi>he called for Famine and the Sword i. e.</hi> he Commanded and Effectuall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cauſed them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.16. <hi>Jer</hi> 25.29.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It is taken for the <hi>Manifeſtatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> of <hi>both,</hi> in diſpenſing Means and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſing his Creature, according to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Right and Dominion he hath ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them as Creatures. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. &amp; 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>I will call them my People which were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> my People</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Here is the <hi>Effect</hi> of this Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Things that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> as though they were.</hi> Not beings aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a manner, are cauſed to be.</p>
                     <p>While ſome underſtand it of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> firſt, others of the Second, I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſee Reaſon, why we may not unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand it of all. And ſo they offer to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Conſideration,</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:137265:19"/>
                     <p n="1">1. The <hi>Omniſciency</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus, our Mediatour.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The <hi>Omnipotency</hi> of our God, in whom we believe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, <hi>The</hi> Omniſciency <hi>of Christ Jeſus our Mediatour. He calleth,</hi> i. e. by his Knowledge foreſeeing all things preſented, as if actually exiſting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; not as exiſting or being in the Divine Nature (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> held their real exiſtence in Eternity, confuted by <hi>Scotus,</hi>) except by way of Eminency: but as to exiſt in time, according to the Will and Wiſdom of the Creator, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.2. <hi>Thou knoweſt my down-ſitting and my up-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, thou underſtandeſt my Thoughts a far off:</hi> and Verſe 6. <hi>Such Knowledge is too wonderful for me, it is high, I cannot attain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t:</hi> i. e. his <hi>Omniſciency.</hi> Unto which add, (leſt any ſhould conceive this to be verified of God the Father only) <hi>John</hi> 21.17. <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hee,</hi> Spoken of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Objected</label> here may be that of the Evang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liſt, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rk</hi> 13.32. <hi>Of that Day and Hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels which are in Heaven, neither the Son, but the Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:137265:20"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> To which I Anſwer; This Text hath puzled many, Ancient and Modern; For reſolution know, 1. That Chriſt did not know that day as he was a Creature; neither was it fit for a Creature to know. Though to Chriſt is granted a Tranſcendent Knowledge: He had a <hi>Created</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, anſwering his ſinleſs Capacity, in his Humane Nature: <hi>Concreated,</hi> by a Participation of the Divine Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; <hi>Infuſed,</hi> neceſſarily following the Hypoſtatical Union. Yea, the Schoolman hath obſerved, that Chriſt had an <hi>acquired</hi> and <hi>experimental</hi> Knowledge, daily gotten by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the active intellect, making ſpecies actually intelligible, abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from the Phantaſms; Yet as man, he knew not that day. There are two things to be conſidered in Chriſt; <hi>viz.</hi> His <hi>Perſon;</hi> and ſo he is Omniſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t: his <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> and ſo he was ſubject to a <hi>Negative</hi> ignorance of ſuch things, whereof the Humane Nature was not capable. <hi>Totus Chriſtus,</hi> was Omniſcient; but not <hi>Totum Chriſti;</hi> he knew as he was God; he did not know as he was man. Neither is it any diſhonour to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:137265:20"/> Chriſt, to have ſuch an ignorance imputed to him, ſince it doth peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly belong to his Humane Nature. But,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We may reſolve the Text thus; that it did not appertain to his Office to teach them of that time; So <hi>Noſce</hi> is put for <hi>Docere;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>I De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to know nothing among you but Chriſt Jeſus and him Crucified.</hi> i. e. to <hi>Preach</hi> any other thing, but Chriſt; his Name and Grace, his Spirit and Love ſhall Triumph in my Diſcourſes to you. For without doubt, then Chriſt knew that day.</p>
                     <p>Now to add more force to our Pen, we will here propound ſome Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the reſolution of which, will yeild great illuſtration to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Q.</label> 
                        <hi>How did Chriſt know?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Not by diſcourſe, as men and Angels do. We know one thing after another, and one thing by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But the Infinite Underſtanding of Chriſt, graſps all things, <hi>Simel et Semel,</hi> at an Inſtant, without any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iw or long Debate; by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Determination of his own Will; all being preſent before him,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:137265:21"/> who is preſent every where. And that for divers Reaſons:</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Becauſe he had the <hi>Idea</hi> of all, and the Reaſon and Ground of all preſent before him. Though the Knowledge here ſpoken of, is not ſo much direct, Intending on the things themſelves; as <hi>Reflex,</hi> by an Act of Intuition on himſelf, the moſt clear glaſs he ſeeth all things in.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Becauſe his Eye was carried from all Eternity, upon and over all; and that by Vertue of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Immenſity of his being. God is in all things, and therefore knows all things. He is a Sphere of Infinite Greatneſs and Efficacy, and whatever is beſides this Sphere, muſt neceſſarily be within it, Encircled and Folded up in it. And hence <hi>David</hi> proves Gods <hi>Omniſciency</hi> by his Omnipreſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134.2.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Effect doth ever vertually pre-exiſt in the Efficient cauſe; either <hi>Formally,</hi> as in Univocal Cauſes, or by way of Eminence, as here. All things known by God, are God, in a more Noble Manner than in themſelves.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>Q.</hi> 2.</label> How can God know things that are not; for <hi>non entis, null eſt Scientia?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:137265:21"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Of no being ſimply, neither in Act nor Power, the Rule is true; but thoſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, not Beings, were then in <hi>eſſe Cognito,</hi> and ſhould certainly be in <hi>eſſe Formali;</hi> He firſt ſeeth them in his own Eſſence, and then blows them into being, by the Breath of his Mouth, by his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding word.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Queſt. 3.</label> 
                        <hi>Whether this do not make ſomething for Equivocation?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Not at all. For, 1. To call things that are not, as though they were, is a Divine Priviledge, men may not do ſo. 2. It is an <hi>Eſſential</hi> Repreſentation, not a <hi>Mental</hi> Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. One thing is not conceived and another called; but things that <hi>are not,</hi> are called, as if they were, which ſhall be in time, as they were known and called before time.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Objected</label> than it may be, <hi>That the Lord foreſaw Sin, as if it had been in Act.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Undoubtedly he did; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to produce and ſuſtain the Act, and permit the obliquity. Which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reflect on God, as if he were the Author of Sin, in not preventing it; For though Sin be the worſt thing in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:137265:22"/> the World, yet the exiſtence of Sin is not Evil, for then God would not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to be. <hi>Proſper</hi> and <hi>Hilary</hi> both, with Renowned <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſay, The Cauſe hereof may be unknown to to us, but unjuſt it cannot it be as God.</p>
                     <p>Which Doctrine offers to us,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Matter of <hi>Information,</hi> in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> of the <hi>Independency</hi> of the Creator, in producing and diſpoſing of the Creature. Nothing out of God did move him to do any thing to them. True it is, that he knew them in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in their Cauſes, and in themſelves; not by Species reſulting from them, but by Reflection on his own Nature. <hi>Extra ſe non quaerit Lumen ut videat, ipſe enim eſt qui videt &amp; unde videt.</hi> He needs not Light from without him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſee by, for he it is that ſeeth, and from himſelf it is that he ſeeth; as <hi>Bernard</hi> expreſſeth it. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>Before I Formed thee in the Womb, I know thee.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, No Love, no Election, no foreſeen Faith or Work: for then they ſhould have been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen in God and not in Man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:137265:22"/> Creature, both in reſpect of Exiſtence and Operation. He calleth thoſe things which are not, as though they were, becauſe of the Neceſſity and Certainty of their being. Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this with Reference to the firſt cauſe. For if we look to ſecond cauſes, there are three ſorts, <hi>viz. Neceſſary,</hi> which cannot but do this and that; as the Fire neceſſarily burneth, and the Sun ſhineth. <hi>Free,</hi> to this or that Act; as the reaſonable Creature is. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent;</hi> beyond Expectation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Effects accordingly: but all known to the firſt Cauſe, before they were, as if they were. So that there is no Room nor need for any <hi>Scientia Media.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> we are Informed how this Divine Omniſcience is a ground of <hi>Faith: viz.</hi> On a Three-fold account.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. As it is known to be <hi>infallible;</hi> his Priviledge that cannot deceive, nor be deceived.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. As it is known to be <hi>Immutable,</hi> ſubject to no Alteration or Variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. he is deſcribed <hi>to be with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut variableneſs or Shadow of Change:</hi> As the Sun, he Shines always with the ſame Rayes of Brightneſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:137265:23"/> (Eclipſes only excepted;) an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that runs through all the reſt; his Mercy, Council, Love, are all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, his Heart is the ſame to day and for ever. We may be Changed in our opinions and Eſtate, but the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature never Changeth.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As it is <hi>Incommunicable.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature is Finite, and this is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite. The Gods of the Gentiles were often herein challenged and found wanting: The firſt Angels would have had it; but ſunk under the weight of that deſire; and <hi>Adams</hi> Candle aſpiring to be a Sun, hath burnt the dimmer ever ſince.</p>
                     <p>All theſe laid together, will prove a ſtrong Motive to believe.</p>
                     <p>In the Second <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of this point, is diſcovered the folly of men, in two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> In endeavouring to prevent Gods Omniſciency, by ſinning ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe ſecretly, and digging deep to hide their Plots. Hear the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.15,16. <hi>We to them that digg deep, to hide their Counſels from the Lord.</hi> They think no eye ſeeth them, not his, who can do nothing but ſee: How vain!
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:137265:23"/> The Eyes of God are like two Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Torches, more reſplendent than the Sun it ſelf; none can ſteal from his Lightning Flaſhes. Screetch-Owls may find Holes and Nights to keep them from the day, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide, but he that flies from the Face of God, where can he find dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enough to hide himſelf? O blind and inſenſible Fugative from the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Eſſence, in the Region of Nothing, whither wilt thou go, not to find the reproaches of thy Crimes! Be Confident, he that can ſave from the deadlieſt extremities, can alſo ſee in the darkeſt obſcurities.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> In endeavouring to uſurp it; and that,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. By manifeſt falſhood not only of the Pope and his adherents, defining and concluding things that are not as though they were; but others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who daringly call their Sins, Gods Temptations; <hi>The Woman thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me,</hi> &amp;c. And many have laid the Baſtards of Hereſie to the door of the Sanctuary, and called Diabolical Seductions, Evangelical Revelations; as if the Father of Lights could bring forth the Iſſues of Death. This
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:137265:24"/> is to uſurp the Royal Prerogative of Heaven, and to invade the Lords In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable Property.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By Flattery; and that either of our ſelves or others. Of our <hi>ſelves;</hi> calling Carnal Contents, Pleaſure, Diſſolute Paſſions, true Mirth; <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs,</hi> Providence; <hi>Vain-Glory,</hi> Curioſity; <hi>Preſumption,</hi> Hope; <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Creatures,</hi> true Riches; againſt our Knowledge. <hi>Solomon</hi> calls them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, things <hi>that are not,</hi> in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of true Riches, Contentment and Duration; for they make to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Wings and flie away as the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle towards Heaven.</hi> Of others; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Great and the Rich; for ſooner will an <hi>hot May</hi> want flies, than ſuch want Flatterers, calling them to be what they are not. Such was that Paraſite who endeavoured to puff up King <hi>Canutus,</hi> by telling him that all his Dominions, nay the Seas themſelves, were at his Command. And <hi>Onuphirus</hi> the Popes Biographer, praiſed <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> or <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, for notable Acts and great Vertues, whom Cardinal <hi>Pembo</hi> true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed to have been a Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, an Adulterer, a Conjurer, every
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:137265:24"/> way as bad as might be. <hi>Mark Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> was a Prince extreamly diſſolute, yet was by his Flatterers called, God <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and he ſoon came to that ſhameful impudence, as to have that title engraved on his Statute. Such ſervile Souls there are, who bind themſelves like Fiſhers Angling Lines, ſeeing their advantages to depend on impertinent Diſcourſe, and that the falſe Altars of Worldly Greatneſs will be ſerved with ſuch Smoke, ſpare it no more than a man would water in a River. No Age, but has been peſtered with ſuch Cattle. <hi>Nero</hi>'s Courtiers would ſooth him up for his ſinging, though it were exceeding ill, with a <hi>Quam pulcher Caeſar Apollo Auguſtus!</hi> Like the Flatterer in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who accomodating himſelf to the time, gave the Ape many ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous praiſes, ſaying, He was a Vermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Roſe, and that thoſe that environ'd him, his Young Ones, were the Leaves; that he was the Sun, and thoſe about him were the Raies; that he was as Valiant as a Lyon, all his off-ſpring were a Race of Young Lyons. With a multitude among our ſelves, who call the niggard, <hi>Bountiful;</hi> the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:137265:25"/> 
                        <hi>Chaſte;</hi> the Proud, <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> the Civil Man, <hi>Religious;</hi> above their Knowledge; they are not ſo we ſee it, neither can we make them ſo, and therefore ſhould not call them ſo,</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3.</label> In the <hi>third</hi> place, this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine yeilds ſingular comfort to all the Faithful. Your Saviour,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Knows all your enemies to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them. <hi>He that ſits in Heaven, Laughs them to ſcorn, the Lord will have them in Deriſion;</hi> be they never ſo cunning and politick; the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence ſhut up in a Cloud, Roareth over their heads, and in a moment will overthrow the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Wind, which the Tyrants of the World raiſe one upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make their ſilly wiſdom appear like an Owl, unfeathered and aſham'd at the Raies of Noon-day; though their al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>itudes may be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Raviſhments to dark the Earth. As it was once ſaid of <hi>Anthony</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſo it may be of Chriſt and the Enemies of his people, His <hi>Geinus</hi> goes beyond theirs.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He knows all our wants to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them; inward, outward, of Soul, Body, for Preſent, for Future
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:137265:25"/> Cheer up your drooping Spirits, in the Conſideration of your Saviour. <hi>In him dwelleth all fulneſs,</hi> as he is Mediatour, eſtabliſhed and deſtinated for your Salvation; ſo that all Perfection, Riches, Grace and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies meet there together, Divinity and Humanity fill'd with all the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Properties that pertain to them, there concur; which Chriſt hath not for himſelf, but for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; as the Sea hath Water, to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey unto the Earth, and the great Luminary hath Brightneſs to Enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Heavens and the Earth, that from it, as from a Common ſource, might Stream forth into all things all the Flame and Warmth they want.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Chriſt knows all your Sins, to Pardon and Subdue them. He cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you now, what you are not; <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Thou art all fair my Love, and there is no Spot in thee.</hi> You ſhall be, becauſe he will make you ſo. Your Light ſhall be without any Shadow, your Beauty without the leaſt Spot to diſgrace it. Thoſe Roſes that are now in their Bloſſom, ſhall be fully blown, and thoſe Stars which are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:137265:26"/> now Impriſoned in a Cloud, ſhall be ſet in a Clear Skie. The Bright Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond of your Souls, now ſoiled with Corruption, ſhall be cleanſed; all the Black Spots now fixt there, ſhall be changed into radiant Lights of Heaven. <hi>Comfort one another with theſe words!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4.</label> 
                        <hi>Laſtly,</hi> We are hence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in ſome few Duties, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. To ſhun inward Sins; Hypocriſie, Pride, Vain-Glory, Infidelity, as carefully as outward and more viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sins. God is Omniſcient, and views the ſins of the heart, as well as the ſins of the Life; the under Roots as well as the upper Boughs. He ſees Faults where men ſee none. Nay, that which ſhines to mans eye like a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, is in Gods Ballance a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Worm. It was a wiſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, therefore, of that <hi>Arabian</hi> we read of, who to prevent ſin, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to himſelf over his head, an Eye which perpetually enlightned him, an Ear which heard him, and an Hand which meaſured out all his Deportments and Demeanours. Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the due conſideration of Gods Eye, will blunt a thouſand and a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:137265:26"/> thouſand Arrows ſhot againſt the heart of a reſolute Chriſtian. If the exerciſe thereof, were as familiar to us, as it is effectual; how power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a motive would it be, to cleanſe all the impurities of our Intentions and affections, and give us leave to arrive to the top of Perfection!</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To ſeek to him for Knowledg. <hi>Ignorance</hi> is no Branch of his Image who is Omniſcient. Let it be the Mother of Popiſh Devotion, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it not ſo much to be with the Profeſſion of Chriſts Religion. He giveth wiſdom <hi>liberally.</hi> He deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Country of Darkneſs, to ſcatter Knowledg by his brightneſs, and ceaſeth not to give light, and kindle in our hearts many Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are like ſo many Stars, to conduct us to the Fountain of our Happineſs. Hear him promiſing, <hi>All thy Children ſhall be taught of God.</hi> It is his Prerogative to teach Hearts. The Sun enlightens the World, and Chriſt enlightens Souls. Make it your Prayer, Lord, breathe upon us; breathe thy Spirit into thy Word! You may read the Bible and hear Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons over and over, but to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:137265:27"/> till the Spirit of Chriſt Shine in your Hearts; and the more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce you have with the Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the more ſplendour you ſhall enjoy. And having obtained, uſe all to his Glory from whom you receive all. Be faithful Stewards. Like as ſmall Rivers, which pay their Tribute and acknowledgments to the great Ocean whence they came.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Prize the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſet an high eſteem upon him: why do we Reverence Learned men among our ſelves, as thoſe eminent Doctors, <hi>Reynolds,</hi> both former and latter; <hi>Perkins, Bolton, Luther, Melancthon, Muſculus, Beza, Calvin, Zanchis, Chamier, Camero</hi> and others? Among our Adverſaries, <hi>Lumbard, Aquinas, Durand, Hales,</hi> &amp;c. Among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Ariſtotle, Plutarch, Homer,</hi> &amp;c. With other brave Fellows, ſeparated from us, by many Lands and Seas, yea, by Death; and all for their Knowledg; becauſe we have ſeen a Ray of their wits upon Paper, Beams of their Knowledg, which was but a drop of his Ocean, and a Spark of his Light, who Enlightneth every one that cometh into the World; this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:137265:27"/> made them admired. If <hi>Alexander</hi> could ſay, That he was more Bound to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his Schoolmaſter, than to his Natural Parent; how much more are we Bound unto and ſhould we Prize and Praiſe our <hi>Omniſcient Jeſus?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> we have here offer'd to our Conſideration, <hi>The Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of our God, in whom we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He calleth; <hi>i. e.</hi> he Cauſeth things not only to appear, but alſo to be in time, as they were willed and ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time;</p>
                     <p>This Power is either <hi>Abſolute;</hi> whereof ſacred writings ſay but little, and about which, we are not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; or <hi>Actual,</hi> as Limited by his Will, and Ordered by his Wiſdom, to give being, and diſpoſe his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by means, to their ſeveral ends. Of which we are now to diſcourſe; giving us two Obſervations; <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>That our God, in whom Abraham believed, and we ſhould belilve, is Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Omnipotency of our God, in whom we ſhould believe, is a firm ground of Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:137265:28"/>
                     <p>For the former; <hi>Our God is Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent.</hi> He can do all things that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply not Imperfection; as to Sin, and deny himſelf: to Sin, is againſt his <hi>Supremacy;</hi> he hath no Superiour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom he might offend; It is againſt his Natural Sanctity and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency. Or, that imply not a Contradiction; as to be and not to be at the ſame time, in the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, becauſe that is Repugnant to Entity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is true of all the Perſons; 1. Of the <hi>Father;</hi> none ever Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging a God, denying it. So we have it in the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>I believe in God, the Father Almighty.</hi> Where, <hi>Almighty,</hi> is applyed to the Father, <hi>Incluſively;</hi> as, Lord, or Dominion is appropriated to the Son, not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Father or the Holy Spirit. Hence it is, that <hi>Hereticks</hi> have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated all the Attributes of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Omniſciency, Omnipotency, to the Father alone.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is true of the <hi>Son.</hi> John 1.3. <hi>All things were made by him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him was nothing made.</hi> Which latter Clauſe, is added for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e more Certainty; it being uſual with the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:137265:28"/> Hebrews, thus by Negation to Confirm, what before they have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, where they would aſſure that the thing is ſo indeed. He is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtiled, <hi>The firſt and the laſt,</hi> Revel. 1.17. It is a verity that is written with the Rays of a vaſt number of Divine Witneſſes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It is true of the Holy Spirit. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. <hi>The Spirit moved on the Face of the Waters; i. e.</hi> he ſuſtained them by the Power of his Sublimity. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Interpreters have varied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, yet all conclude it to be the Spirit of God, nothing diſtinct from the Deity, or Infinite Active Power of God. So the Pſalmiſt, 95 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> which our Apoſtle takes notice of, as ſpoken not <hi>by,</hi> but <hi>of</hi> the Holy Spirit; <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.7.</p>
                     <p>The Grounds whereof are two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Unity of Nature doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, equality of Power; we ſay, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there are three Subſiſtences in the Divine Eſſence, and that each of thoſe Perſons, is truely and properly God: and we find ſuch Attributes and works aſcribed to the whole Nature of the Deity, to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:137265:29"/> Perſons Subſiſting in that Divine Nature, as do evince their Power to be the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This Manifeſtation of power, is <hi>opus ad extra,</hi> and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: According to that conſtant Rule of Credit among all Divines, <hi>Opera Trinitatis ad extr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſunt indiviſa:</hi> But eſpecially Attributed to the Second Perſon here and in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; becauſe that is moſt benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the Church, and is moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Poſed by Enemies. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>I am God Almighty, [Elſhaddai,]</hi> ſignifying, either <hi>Sufficiency,</hi> becauſe he is ſufficient of himſelf, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 16.2. <hi>My Goodneſs extendeth not to thee,</hi> &amp;c. He is Infinitely above Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; Infinite in Eſſence and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, comprehending within himſelf all good, and anticipating it to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with an incomparable Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Or elſe, it ſignifieth, <hi>Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> (for the word will bear both) all things yielding to him, both for their being, order and continuance. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.14. <hi>Is there any thing too hard for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rd?</hi> Numb. 23.19. <hi>God is not as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n that he ſhould lie, neither the Son of Man, that he ſhould Repent;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:137265:29"/> hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not do it?</hi> Mat. 19.26. <hi>With God all things are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But what need of proof? It is a truth written as with Rayes of the Sun; confirm'd at leaſt 70 times in the Scriptures of God, as ſome have taken pains to reckon them. Add we may,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Confeſſion and practice of the Saints of God in all Ages; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. <hi>O our God wilt thou not judge them?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.9. <hi>God hath power to help and to caſt down.</hi> Flying from their Enemies both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to reſt upon his Rock of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. <hi>I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.57. <hi>O Death where is thy Sting!</hi> Thanks be to God through Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The works of Chriſt; Curing the Diſeaſed; <hi>Mark</hi> 5.26,27. <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> the Temple, <hi>Math.</hi> 21.12,13. Which <hi>Jerom</hi> Attributes to his <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency;</hi> that he ſo mean, ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt a matter ſo conſiderable, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo many proud, inſolent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, arm'd with Authority, and at ſuch a time; and extolls it above rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the Dead, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring</hi>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:137265:30"/> the Blind to ſight, and the Lame to their Limbs. This was his Divine Work. Not to omit the mentioning of his Changing Water into Wine; <hi>John</hi> 27.</p>
                     <p>Thus as the greatneſs of the Sun is meaſured by a ſmall Shadow on the Earth, ſo many times there needs but few words to illuſtrate a great Vertue.</p>
                     <p>The Reaſons are many, I ſhall chuſe out and inſiſt upon two only:</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Unitie of Nature common to all the Perſons, <hi>John</hi> 17.22. <hi>As we are one. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num per <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem;</hi> i. e. by the abſolute ſimplicitie of Nature. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Who — Reckoned himſelf e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with God,</hi> in that incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible abundance of Perfection, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſupream Adorable Nature is full; as Life, Goodneſs, Immenſity, Eternity, Holineſs, and all other Properties, which it hath in an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible manner. Now from the purity and Perfection of that Infinite Being, we may thus argue for <hi>Omnipotency, viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That which hath Being and is moſt diſtant from Paſſive Power, being</hi> Ens Simpliſſimum, &amp; Actus puriſſimus, <hi>a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:137265:30"/> most Simple Being, and a moſt pure Act, muſt partake Infinitely of Active Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> which is <hi>Omnipotency,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Again; <hi>In whom is found the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all things, in him is alſo found the Perfection of Power: But in Chriſt is found the Perfection of all things, Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently,</hi> as is already proved, therefore in him, is the Perfection of Power; which is <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> to which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be added.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Equality of Attributes; as is his Knowledge, ſo is his Will and Power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.6. <hi>Whatſoever the Lord pleaſed, that did he in Heaven and Earth.</hi> Now Knowledg and Power, are according to the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Nature; Men know and can do ſomething; <hi>Angels</hi> know and can do more; but God moſt of all, his Knowledg is Infinite, and ſo muſt his Power needs be.</p>
                     <p>The Second Doctrine from hence, now comes to hand, <hi>viz. That this is a Principal Ground of Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Without Faith it is Impoſſible to pleaſe God; for he that cometh to God, muſt believe that he is, and that he is a Rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:137265:31"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. When God would encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <hi>Abraham,</hi> he maketh himſelf known by the glorious Attribute of his Almighty Power; <hi>I am God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient.</hi> Math. 8.2. <hi>Lord if thou wilt, thou canst make me Clean.</hi> There is no ſuch proper Pillar to uphold a falling Spirit, as this of the power of God; No Shade like to this, to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward off the ſtrokes of Evil. One Shine of this Attribute in its full Luſtre of Glory, is able to diſpell in a moment, all the nights of Fear, Doubts, Temptations, which may at any time overſpread the Heaven of the Soul, it cauſeth them utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vaniſh. Here's the Adaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Bulwark againſt all Adverſary Power. <hi>The Devil is Mighty, but not Almighty, as my God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is;</hi> was that comforted <hi>Luther,</hi> that Incarnate Seraphin, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>How it is ſo, will further appear, if we conſider,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The <hi>Difficulty</hi> of things offer'd, both for matter and manner. As that all things ſhould be ours again, after they were loſt; that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane Nature ſhould be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:137265:31"/> united; that a Virgin ſhould Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and Bear a Son; what great and admirable things are theſe? Here are matters which the cleereſt Underſtandings of Men and Angels entertain with Amazement, things in a Sphere above Nature, beyond all Humane Diſquiſition; <hi>The deep things of God;</hi> the Divine <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency</hi> can only maintain Faith in the ſenſe of their poſſibility.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. His <hi>Propriety</hi> in and over all. He made all, gave them a Being according to the <hi>Idea</hi> and Platform preſented to the Divine Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and he hath abſolute Right to diſpoſe of all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>To do with his own as he will.</hi> His Power is independent, and Prerogative il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.6. to be underſtood of <hi>Chriſt; Thou madeſt him to have Dominion over the works of thine Hands.</hi> Which <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not from the nature of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative Bounty,</hi> in beſtowing Gifts, to ſome more, to others leſs, and ſo hath more or leſs Right over them; for then his Power ſhould be finite and limited, as (<hi>Arminians</hi> hold, only to cut off the Abſolute
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:137265:32"/> Decree, which the Lord paſt by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Right) no Creature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable of an Infinite meaſure of goodneſs: But from the <hi>Excellency of his Nature,</hi> being Omniſcient, Omnipotent, Infinite, Eternal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. From the <hi>Irreſiſtability</hi> of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: All things do obey him. There is nothing from Heaven to Hell which boweth not under his Laws. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19. <hi>Who hath reſiſted his Will?</hi> Luke 7.7,8. <hi>Say the words, and thy Servant ſhall he Healed.</hi> And this is true of Chriſt, as appears <hi>Math</hi> 8.27. <hi>Even the Winds and the Seas obey him. Xerxes</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch, threw Fetters into the Sea, as if he would have Chained the unruly Waves; but to little purpoſe; but when Chriſt ſpeaks, <hi>The Winds and the Seas ſhall obey him.</hi> By a word he unpins the Wheels and breaks the Axle-Tree of the whole Creation. In ſhort, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Divine Unerſtanding can Comprehend, ſo much the Divine Power can Execute.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. From the <hi>Incommunicableneſs</hi> of this Attribute. No Creature is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being Omnipotent: <hi>&amp; quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid recipitur, ad modum Recipientis,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:137265:32"/> Recipitur.</hi> Beſides every Creature is Reſiſtable in the Exerciſe of Natural Qualities. <hi>In him we Live and move and have our Being:</hi> he Supports, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains, and orders all.</p>
                     <p>But here we meet with Objections from ſome, who, Imitating the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, caſt miſts upon the Brighteſt Morning.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>1 Object.</label> 
                        <hi>May not this Omnipotency be Imputed to the Humane Nature of Chriſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> By Reaſon of the Union Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatical, the Properties of both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may be Communicated to the Perſon, and yet not mutually between the Natures. The Natures were not Changed, nor their Properties Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, each Retaining after, what was peculiar before Chriſt ſuffered and Dyed, but according to his Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Chriſt was Omniſcient and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, but according to his Deity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>2 Object.</label> 
                        <hi>Is raiſed from that Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of Chriſt himſelf, Math.</hi> 28.18. <hi>All Power is given me in Heaven and in Earth;</hi> which ſay ſome, cannot be underſtood of his Deity, for ſo he was not Capable of any Addition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> It is ſpoken of Chriſt as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:137265:33"/> Mediator. Omnipotency was given to him for Interceſſion, and Aplication of his Merits, for the Governing and gathering of his Saints; <hi>That all things ſhall work together for good:</hi> ſo, <hi>John</hi> 5.22. <hi>The Father judgeth no man, but hath Committed all Judgment to the Son;</hi> and for other Places of that Nature, they are to be underſtood, not Simply of <hi>Power,</hi> but of <hi>Authority;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24,25. <hi>Then the End ſhall come, when he ſhall have delivered up the Kingdom to God even the Father, when he ſhall have put down all Rule and all Authority and Power; for he muſt Reign till he hath Subdued all his Enemies under his Feet.</hi> Which eſtabliſheth the former anſwer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>3. Object.</label> 
                        <hi>Is it not Communicated to Believers?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Chriſt hath given very great Power to Believers, in ſo much as 1. Believers <hi>can do all things;</hi> but then ſee whence their bow hath ſuch a back of Steel, <hi>viz,</hi> in and from Chriſt, by a derived Power. Chriſt leaves on ſuch as have received him, ſome foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps and Impreſſions of his <hi>Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency:</hi> for, whereas <hi>Divine Power</hi> Conſiſts eſpecially in two things <hi>viz.</hi>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:137265:33"/> In Gods being able to do all things that are Regularly poſſible, and his not being able to do any thing Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; ſo, we find ſome Prints of both upon Chriſtians; <hi>I can do all things,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul; And whoſoever is born of God cannot Sin,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>John:</hi> this I ſay, is by a derived Power, Communicated to them according to their Capacity.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. All things are poſſible to them; <hi>i. e.</hi> all things as Chriſt was to do for them, or they receive from him as Mediator; <hi>all things are poſſible to them,</hi> not <hi>Simply,</hi> but <hi>Reſpectively</hi> to that Power, unto which all things are Referr'd and Subjected.</p>
                     <p>Well then; to apply the whole.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1.</label> 
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Diverſe Corolaries may be deduced from the whole, by way of <hi>Information,</hi> viz.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That he in whom we believe, Jeſus Chriſt, God bleſſed for ever, was before all things that now have being, and gave being to all. <hi>John</hi> 8.58. <hi>Before Abraham was, I am.</hi> John 1.2. <hi>The ſame was in the Beginning;</hi> in the Inſtant of Creation, therefore alſo, before the Creation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from Eternity. Indeed <hi>Arrius</hi>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:137265:34"/> Corrupts the Greek Text, reading it thus, <hi>The Lord Created me in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;</hi> and thence Blaſphemouſly Inferr'd, that Chriſt was no more than a Creature. But the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He was ſet up from Everlaſting;</hi> Prov. 8.23. and he is called, <hi>The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of Days, Dan.</hi> 7.9. And as he was before all things, ſo he <hi>gave being</hi> to all things; 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. He was not Idle with the Father (as ſome Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly ſpeak) but by him as a Principal Efficient, co-Agent, the Father and Holy Ghoſt, all things were made.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That all things (Creatures) which we ſee and know, once were not, and are in the Power of God to be Reduced into nothing; or to be Diſpoſed by him, as he ſhall pleaſe, according to his Abſolute Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. God hath Power over every Created being, and over every part of being; He being <hi>Jehovah,</hi> that gave being to all and received being from none. He Confirms Scepters and Crowns; he Raiſeth Cities, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and Monarchies; he erects States, preſerves Laws, and Travels through-out all Nature without take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:137265:34"/> pains; and can as eaſily Reduce them all to nothing.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That there is an exact Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity between the Decree and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. Things that had no being, were called as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> they had been, and in time they were, as they were before called. There is no depending Freedom in any Creature: God ſuſtains the Agent, and determins the Action; his Power reacheth over all.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That God cannot Sin, for he is Omniſcient and cannot err; he is Omnipotent and hath no paſſive Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to receive from without, that might change his will. Ever is to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Blaſphemous Doctrine of the <hi>Marcionites, Manichees,</hi> and <hi>Libertines,</hi> who would make this Dreadful and Sacred Majeſty the Cauſe of moſt deteſtable Errours; yet with as much abſurdity as they, who make the Sun Guilty of Darkneſs, by whom the Heaven is enlightned; and the Sea of Drineſs, by whom the whole Earth is Moiſtned. And therefore Conclude againſt <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> who Wickedly Imputed to Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that which they Deteſt with greateſt Loathing.</p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:137265:35"/>
                     <p n="5">5. That we have the ſame ground for our Faith as <hi>Abraham</hi> had, viz. the <hi>Omnipotency</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſeen in the Creation of the World, and Suſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of all, in bearing with all; in the great Empire and Defence of the Church and Goſpel, in the midſt of Enemies; in Converting, Pardoning Sin, and Preſerving all his Houſe from Apoſtacy; In all which you have a Marvellous Diſcovery of his Divine Power, who maketh Light to break out of Darkneſs, and Traces the Rays of his Glory upon an heap of Dirt, uſing baſe and Inferiour Perſons and things, for the good of his People.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Therefore we ſhould not Finally doubt nor deſpair of our ſelves or others, <hi>Math.</hi> 19.26. <hi>With God all things are poſſible.</hi> Rom. 11.32. <hi>God is able to Graft them in again.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his third Epiſtle to <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſian,</hi> and elſe-where, give Rules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſtruſtful Reaſonings; <hi>Tota ratio facti, Potentia Facientis; Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra Authorem, tolle Dubitationem.</hi> We muſt grant God to be able to do ſome things, the Reaſon of which we are not able to Comprehend; the whole Reaſon of doing, being the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:137265:35"/> Power of the Doer: it is God that doth them; Conſider the Author, and all doubts will ceaſe. Let us Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Paul <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mary Magdalen, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ſſes,</hi> and other Monuments of Gods Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which hath Crowned Plants with Flowers and Fruits, that were Barren and Accurſed; fill'd Deſarts and the moſt Deſolate Heaths, with Exquiſite and Delicate Trees; which Examples had never come to our Hearing, had it not been for our Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. With theſe ſhould every Sound Penitent be Revived and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. God can turn Noiſom Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills into a Mine of Gold, Brands of Hell into Lightſome Stars, in the higheſt Firmament; Slaves of <hi>Daemons</hi> into Angels.</p>
                     <p>Doubt not, Deſpair not of the Church and State. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.11,12. <hi>O my People, I will open your Graves, and cauſe you to come out of your Graves.</hi> What cannot God do, who can Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate? Nothing can ſtand before a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Power. He needeth no exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Matter to work upon, nor Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Work with. O, what a great thing is nothing in the Hand of God!</p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:137265:36"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</label> 
                        <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ondly,</hi> this Doctrine ſounds ſharp reproof againſt thoſe, 1. Who abuſe this Atribute either in opinion or practiſe. In,</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Opinion,</label> as they who argue <hi>a Poſſe ad eſſe,</hi> becauſe of the power of God; and Attribute that to it, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a Contradiction; as to be a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Body in Subſtance, and yet Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in Preſence, to be every where. It is Chriſts Divine Property to be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> many places at once, neither inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively nor excluſively. If it be ſaid, That the Omnipotency of God may extend the Dimenſions of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that it may at the ſame time fill Heaven and Earth; it may be eaſily replied, This is to make Chriſt a Monſter, and to contradict the very Nature of a Created Body. Yet Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts moſt confidently obtrude this Principle upon the Word, and by this their Catholick Power, make a Body to be at two places at once; as the Body of Chriſt in Heaven, and upon a popiſh Altar at once: Which is a contradiction, and therefore a lye. <hi>Let God be true and every man a Lyar.</hi> Heaven is ſaid to to receive Chriſts Body, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. In</p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:137265:36"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>Practice;</label> As they, <hi>Firſt,</hi> who live as if they were Omnipotent. Such there be in the World, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make their Will a Law, and cauſe all to fall down before them. Like <hi>Jezebel</hi> and <hi>Sennacharib;</hi> confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Elements, and raiſing Stars with the Duſt of the Earth, whereby to come to the end of their exhorbitant pretenſions; Threatning to hew down Mountains, and Thunder-ſtrike Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals; ſuppoſing all the ample houſe of Nature to be Created for them. Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the World by Avarice, and waſting it by Riot. And not only ſo, but according to the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Cruel Pride, cry not, with the Old Tyrant, for another World to plunder, but attempt the Invaſion of the Intelligible World, and commit Rapine upon Souls, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king havock of the Church of God, to which Angels refer but as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Spirits; and Lording it over Gods Heritage, which the Apoſtles <hi>beſought</hi> to be <hi>Reconciled to God,</hi> and never Commanded them any thing, in their own name, and only ſuch things, for which, they could ſhew unqueſtionable Commiſſion. Such as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:137265:37"/> theſe ſet themſelves down in the Throne of God, as <hi>Maximilian</hi> that good Emperour uſed to ſay; this being one of thoſe three things, the Divine Power hath reſerved to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as his Prerogative, <hi>viz.</hi> To Create, to Foretel things to come, and to Rule over Conſciences. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> Living as if they cared not for him that is Omnipotent, indeed deſpiſing his Threatnings, ſlighting his Promiſes, as if he were able to perform neither. Whence they dare to lift an Arm againſt the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent! When as all power in Heaven and in Earth, yea, all Judgment is committed to Chriſt. He hath Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to relieve his Saints, to Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence all his Enemies unto Eternal Flames and Torments; and will make ſome as bright as Stars, and others like Burning Coals in Hell. O Hear, Conſider, Tremble!</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This Doctrine caſteth a ſharp Dart of reproof againſt all ſuch that deny or doubt of it: as thoſe <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Can the Lord provide Fleſh alſo?</hi> And that Court-Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.2. Who, when the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> by the Command of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:137265:37"/> God, foretold the great Plenty of <hi>Samaria,</hi> dared to ſay, <hi>If the Lord open the Windows of Heaven, can theſe things be?</hi> Such unbelieving hearts are among us to this day. Can the Lord do this or that? Is he able to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh what he hath promiſed, can he Heal my Backſlidings, pardon my Sins, and ſave my Soul? As if the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> lived after the rate of Creatures. This is to reproach the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Againſt ſuch as rely altogether on the Power of God, without the uſe of Means. As the former ſort <hi>Reproach</hi> God, ſo theſe <hi>Tempt</hi> God. The Lord could indeed Enlighten us without the Sun, and afford us Fruit without the Earth; but he will have the Creature Operate. The very Heathen could ſay, <hi>Admota manu, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocanda eſt Minerva;</hi> and the Sage Greek, Rebuked the fooliſh Carter, who, when his Waggon ſtuck in the Mud, Cryed to God, but never put his hand to help himſelf: Meanes muſt be uſed. Though men live not by Bread alone, but by the word of Gods Bleſſing proceeding out of his Mouth, yet that word is Annexed to <hi>Bread,</hi>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:137265:38"/> and not to Stones: and that man ſhould not <hi>Truſt</hi> but Tempt God, who would have Stones turned into Bread, becauſe God hath Power ſo to do. And if God have provided ſtairs it is not <hi>Faith</hi> but <hi>Fury,</hi> not <hi>Confidence</hi> but <hi>Madneſs</hi> to go down a Precipice. Second Means muſt be uſed in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods order, though not in Confidence of their help; the Creature muſt be the Object of our <hi>Dilligence,</hi> but God only the Object of our <hi>Truſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3.</label> 
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This Doctrine, as it is ſufficient to terrify the Wicked, ſo it is to give occaſion of Confidence to the <hi>Faithful;</hi> ſince it hath an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal alliance with him that governs the World. Read your matchleſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, in the following particulars.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Againſt Sin, Satan and all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Church, that Chriſt is Omnipotent, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.15. In the Words of King <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Judah, Thus ſaith the Lord to you, Be not afraid or diſmayed becauſe of this great Multitude, for the Battel is not yours but Gods.</hi> 2 Chron. 32.7,8. <hi>Hezekiah ſaid to the People, Be ſtrong and Couragious, be not Afraid or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, for the Kings of Aſſyria, nor for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:137265:38"/> the Multitude that is with them, for they are more with us than with them.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Power or Counſel ſhall be ſet up againſt Heaven, ſhall not ſucceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deſign of Heaven. The vaſt Numbers of men, trouble him no more, than thoſe Millions of Waves in the Sea, are a trouble to that great Ocean. All Nations before him, are but as one drop of the Dew. He Cauſeth whole Countries to tremble under the Force of his Word, as under Lightning Arrows; and is attired with the Conqueſt and Trophies of Souls. O the Wonders of God! He Cauſeth the Arrows of thoſe that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade his Kingdom, to Return againſt them that ſhot them; as in <hi>Julian</hi>'s Caſe was apparent; which we only mention. Though he thought by the help of his falſe Gods, to Command the Waves of the Sea, and to walk upon the Stars, yet was he buried in Execration and Horrours.</p>
                     <p>And as it is in Temporals, ſo it is in Spirituals. He can ſubdue the ſtrongeſt Corruptions, Break the hardeſt Heart, relieve the moſt Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Graces. Let all Chriſts People learn to look up, and then you will,</p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:137265:39"/>
                     <p n="1">1. Patiently ſuffer and wait. He is Omniſcient and Omnipotent; He knows all and can relieve all.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. You will learn to reſt upon him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 37.3. <hi>Truſt in the Lord and do good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the Land.</hi> You will not truſt in men and frame to your ſelves an arm of Straw; but confide in him, who with the Fingers of his Power ſuſtains the whole Globe of the Earth. You will not Adore the Favours of men, which are like the Rainbow in Heaven, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made ſhew of many Splendours and varied Paintings, leaves nothing but Water and Morter. You will then no more build Fortunes on Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Silver, upon a Frail man, who beareth all the Fingers of Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. God is a Wall of Braſs about his people. <hi>Lo I am with you to the end of the World!</hi> In all Conditions. If <hi>Daniel</hi> be in the Lyons Den, he ſhall be viſited by God, and the Lyons change their Nature, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to him. If the three worthieſt be caſt into the Fiery Furnace, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzars</hi> Hell, they ſhall walk entire, aſſiſted by the Angel of God, as in a Meadow Enameld over with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:137265:39"/> Flowers: And now, when, one would have thought, that whole Religion had been dead, the Divine Power Writes her Praiſes in Characters of Fire. Whoever forſakes the Lords People, he will not forſake them. He is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This Doctrine ſpeaks ſingular Comfort againſt loſſes, of Country, Friends, Eſtate, Liberty, and all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Comforts; if you be in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him that is Omnipotent. This was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Caſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17 1. <hi>Fear not Abraham, I am thy Shield; I am God Almighty, or All-ſufficient;</hi> before whom nothing can ſtand when he will accompliſh his Word. This was a bottom of great Confidence to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Being fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> &amp;c. Where ever God is engaged by his Word, his Power is eſpecially to be eyed. Perſons are apt to ask, How can theſe things be? It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould be ſo and ſo to us; but he is able, Omnipotent. It is he that made <hi>Joſephs</hi> Abaſements to be his Advancements; and that turn'd <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> Curſe into a Bleſſing. He can
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:137265:40"/> bring Meat out of the Eater, and Sweet out of the Strong, and cauſe Grapes to be gathered of Thorns, and Figs from Thiſtles, make Friends of Enemies, your Wound your Cure, your Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, your Conſolation. Nay, your Weakneſs, your Strength. So that as the ſame Water is ſowre in the juice of a Figtree, is ſweet in the fruit; ſo the Troubles which in their bark are but ſowre and unpleaſing, ſhall not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in the fruit of them be exceeding ſweet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4.</label> 
                        <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Be ye Inſtructed to be followers of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in this Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Age of the World: to build on this Foundation, in your Obedience both Active and Paſſive.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Be perſwaded of this Truth, Meaſure not God by the Ell of man, Cloath him not in your Faſhion. Hold not that Impoſſible to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, what your weak Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot Apprehend. Be perſwaded,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he is able to caſt down the Strongeſt and Proudeſt Enemies of his Kingdom: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.29. <hi>Becauſe thy Rage againſt me and thy Tumult is come up into mine Ears, therefore will I put mine Hook into thy Noſe, and my
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:137265:40"/> Bridle in thy Lips,</hi> &amp;c. When the Rage and Tumult of Chriſts Adverſaries is higheſt, then will he get himſelf moſt Glory, by putting a Hook in their Noſtrils, and turning them as he pleaſeth. Can any thing be too hard for God? this God of Power, who Darkneth the Air with Tempeſts, makes Clouds to pour down in Deluges, and Swallows up the Fleets of petty <hi>Pharo</hi>'s? He who flyeth upon wings of the Wind, over the Curling Waters of the Sea, Inflaming Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and makes Blood and Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Rain on the Rebels of the Earth?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> That he is able to Raiſe out of the loweſt Condition. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>Job</hi> on the Dunghill, <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Chriſtians of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, and all along, whence they were ready to cry out, <hi>There is no Hope.</hi> His Power and Eſſence walk Hand in Hand; in ſo much, as Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in God is nothing elſe but the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Eſſence of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Object.</label> 
                        <hi>We all believe Gods Power, but doubt of his Will.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> All do not believe his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. The <hi>unregenerate</hi> man believes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:137265:41"/> not at all. All unbelief doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly queſtion the Power of God. And <hi>Renewed</hi> men believe not <hi>Fully.</hi> Things paſt and preſent, all can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, becauſe they are ſeen, but things promiſed, becauſe they Tranſcend the Courſe of natural Cauſes, and the Contrivances and Projects which they forecaſt, they often Flag and Falter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. They limit him in their thoughts, they will have ſuch and ſuch Graces, ſo much in the uſe of Means, and ſuch Means, thoſe of their own Choice, rather than others; whereas God is an Independing Agent, and works where, when, and as he will. As God is Omnipotent to Command Supplies for any help, ſo he is Abſolute to Chuſe what Means he pleaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and his Wiſdom ſhall pitch upon.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. They Determine and often Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude againſt themſelves, and raſhly too, and againſt their preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; being brought to ſome extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, they drew up deſperate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions againſt Mercy it ſelf, ſaying, <hi>The Lord will be gracious no more; I</hi> ſhall ſurely fall by the ſtrength of this
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:137265:41"/> Corruption and that Temptation. <hi>Mrs. Honywoods</hi> Caſe is famous; who confidently affirm'd, ſhe ſhould be Damn'd, as ſure as that Glaſs would break, that ſhe threw againſt the wall. And <hi>David</hi> in his haſte ſaid, <hi>I am cut off from before thine Eyes.</hi> If they are advanced, then they ſhall never be caſt down; <hi>David</hi> alſo in ſuch a Caſe could ſay, <hi>My Mountain ſhall never be moved:</hi> good News lifts them up, and ill News caſts them down. It argueth a great Defect, in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the heart with God, who is both powerful and willing.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Make uſe of this Doctrine and Truth delivered about Chriſts <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency,</hi> theſe three ways, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> in your Faith to believe his Word. Prophecies ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, Promiſes be fulfilled. Anti-Chriſt ſhall fall. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.7. <hi>Thou ſhalt break, them with a Rod of Iron,</hi> &amp;c. Ezek. 24.14. <hi>I the Lord have ſpoken it, it ſhall come to paſs.</hi> Accordingly when the Seven Angels appeared with the ſeven laſt Plagues, <hi>they that ſtood on the Sea of Glaſs, ſaid in their Song, Great and Marvellous are thy Works, Lord God Almighty,</hi> &amp;c. And when
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:137265:42"/> the third of them poured out his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol upon the Rivers of Water, an Angel of the Altar ſaid, <hi>Even ſo Lord God Almighty,</hi> &amp;c. So that all who wiſh well to <hi>Sion,</hi> make full account, that in due time <hi>the Mountain of the Lord ſhall be ſet upon the top of all Mountains,</hi> becauſe it hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed of old, and be confident, as it is expreſſed in 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>That the wicked one ſhall be conſumed by the Breath of his Mouth,</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe this Commination ſtandeth upon the file in Holy Scripture, and is not yet verified. Though God do not allways fulfill his Threatnings, but on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance revoke them; yet he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes fulfills his Promiſes to them that fear him and hope in his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> in your Prayers, to Crave his Aid and Aſſiſtance. <hi>Whatever ye ask the Father in my name, he will give it you.</hi> Let men be never ſo prone, the Carnal Appetite uniting with a probable Object, being able of it ſelf no more to Reſiſt, than a Stone can from Deſcending, or the Adamant from Drawing, yet the Lord can Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, Renew, do away all old things,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:137265:42"/> and make all to become New. <hi>To whome ſhall we go? Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</hi> From his eyes alone, are darted Rayes of moſt Powerful Compaſſions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In your Patience under any of his Rods, and Diſeaſes Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Spiritual, Political. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.20. <hi>He is able to do abundantly above all, what we are able to ask or think.</hi> It is a tried Caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>I will not be afraid of ten Thouſands of People that have ſet themſelves againſt me round about.</hi> O ſay, Fie upon Deſpair and minds Affliction! Learn in all things that appertain to you, ſpeedily and Effectually to fix your ſelves on the Will of the Omnipotent. Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſay, God ſeeth this Affair, ſince nothing eſcapeth the Quickneſs of his Eye. Expect but a while, the Trouble is but a Flying Cloud, and God will do all for the beſt. Thus did <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Text; <hi>Above Hope he believed in Hope,</hi> becauſe God <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Dead, and calleth things that are not, as though they were.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:137265:43"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>Verſ. 18.</bibl>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Who againſt Hope, Believed in Hope. —</hi>
                           </p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THeſe words Contain a lively <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, drawn from the <hi>Internal Form,</hi> it was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, A Phraſe Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be underſtood, but moſt aptly ſerves to ſhew the Difficulty of believing. Some turn the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> by <hi>Praeter,</hi> beſides hope; others, by <hi>Supra,</hi> above Hope; a third ſort, by <hi>Abſque,</hi> without. All may be true, but not reach ſo fully Home, neither to the Word nor Scope of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Our laſt Tranſlation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, following many, both Antient and Modern Divines, Reads it, <hi>Againſt;</hi> and ſo I find ſome Refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To the time of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith; in the beginning of his Age he had hope, but this was againſt that. In the middle of his Age he complain'd, as if there were no hope; <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Lord what wilt thou give me, ſince I go childleſs?</hi> But this was after that.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Others refer it to the kinds of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:137265:43"/> hope, or degrees of one and the ſame hope; whom I rather chooſe to follow.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> underſtand it was ſpoken of two Kinds of Hope; one <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural,</hi> when Reaſon apprehends Grounds why ſuch a thing may be; and this is proportionably common to men with Beaſts. Another <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine;</hi> when a man waits for that he can ſee no ground in himſelf, nor reaſon for. <hi>Abraham</hi> was againſt the firſt, and in the ſecond.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Others take it for one and the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me hope, but in different degrees, It was weak and doubtful in the beginning but ſtrong and firm in the end. Faith and Hope (two individual companions; Hope ſpringing from Faith, as the Stream from the Fountain, or the Daughter from the Mother) meet with many oppoſitions, but prove victorious in the end. Yeilding us three things Right Worthy of Obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>The Connexion of theſe two Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Graces, Believing in Hope.</hi> Rom. 5.2. <hi>By whom alſo we have Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs by Faith into this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>race wherein we ſtand, and rejoice in Hope of the Glory of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:137265:44"/> God.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>By whom we do believe in God that raiſed him from the Dead and gave him Glory, that your [Faith and Hope] might be in God.</hi> The Sun and the Beams go together, and ſo do <hi>Faith and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Reaſons are, 1. They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed at once, when the Spirit is given to the Elect, as they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it, before, in, or after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. What they ſay of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Vertues, <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t inter ſe conn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xae,</hi> they are chain'd together, may be alſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id of the Graces of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nts an habit of all the Graces in the Heart. The <hi>New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll the Parts and Lineaments, a mixture of all the Humours.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. From the order and maner of Working; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> begette h ſtirreth up and manifeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> it ſelf by ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>her. Rom. 5 3,4. <hi>And not only ſo, but we Glory in Tribulations alſo, knowing that Tribul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ion work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>th Patience; and Patience, Experience; and Exeperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>p;</hi> &amp;c. Faith there is a Mother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>cended with her Daughters. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15 13. <hi>The God of Hope fill you w th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll Joy and Peace in believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that you may abound in Hope.</hi> 1 Cor.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:137265:44"/> 13.7. <hi>Charity believeth all things, Hopeth all things,</hi> &amp;c. Heb. 12.1. <hi>Faith is the Subſtance of things not ſeen.</hi> Faith lights the Lamp to hope, as the Fire of the Altar lighted the Lamps of the Sanctuary.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We are hence to obſerve, <hi>the Difficulty of believing;</hi> it is <hi>againſt Hope.</hi> Math. 19.13. <hi>a Rich man can hardly Enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This appears divers wayes; <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Efficient</hi> neceſſarily required to work Faith in the Heart. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.19. It is called the <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſs of his Power to us-ward who believe.</hi> A Difficult Work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a great Power to accompliſh it. Man, as <hi>Clem. Alexandrinus</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, is Gods Harp; the Harp cannot ſound unleſs it be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the finger, neither can the Heart of man ſound forth any Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Harmony, till it be touched by the Finger of Gods Spirit; Sin having diſorder'd the Strings of that Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Inſtrument, put it out of Tune, and mar'd its Muſick, and there is nothing but Jarring; and ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues, till that great Muſician, who
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:137265:45"/> tunes the whole World and makes all things keep time and meaſure, ſet this Inſtrument in Tune again.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. From the Paucity of Believers. <hi>Iſa</hi> 58.1. <hi>Who hath believed our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> &amp;c. Luke 18.8. <hi>When the Son of man cometh, ſhall he find Faith on the Earth?</hi> Among the Millions at <hi>Rome,</hi> there were but few Senators; and among the ſwarms of People in the World, there are but few Beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. In themſelves, indeed Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they are many, as the Stars which adorn the Azure Firmament, as the Sands on the Sea ſhore for Multitude; but Comparatively, they are very few. As in the Field there are more Weeds than ſweet Flowers, and in the Earth more Droſs than Gold; Thus it is here. The Trees of Righteouſneſs are thinly Planted in the Worlds Orchard. There are but few Birds of Paradiſe, to the Birds of Prey: Notwithſtanding all the Means of Grace, Preaching, Exhorting, Reading, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> few Believers.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. From the many Enemies of Faith, and other Impediments; There is <hi>Satan, Luke</hi> 22.31. <hi>Satan hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ow you as Wheat, but I have
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:137265:45"/> prayed, that thy Faith fail not.</hi> This is the main thing he aims at, This he Aſſaults, endeavouring to blind-fold the Eye of Judgment; to allure the Will and Affections after Toys, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Profits and worldly Honours: perſwading ſometime to preſume, other-while driving to Deſpair. Thus he ſifts and Winnows poor Souls, to keep them in Unbelief, or Misbeleif. There is the <hi>World of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate men,</hi> as the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> watching to catch our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour that they might accuſe him; Concluding, if any man did Confeſs Chriſt, he ſhould be put out of the Synagogue, <hi>John</hi> 9.22. Yea, for a time, <hi>Paul,</hi> a Choſen Veſſel, was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as an Inſtrument that way; <hi>Acts</hi> 28.23. <hi>Concerning this Sect, it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt every where.</hi> A great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement. Yea, our own <hi>Natural Abilities,</hi> which are Antipodes to Grace; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wiſe, they became Fools.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.22. <hi>The Jews Require a Sign, the Greeks ſeek after Wiſdom;</hi> not that which <hi>cometh from above;</hi> by <hi>Wiſdom</hi> they could not come to the Knowledg of God, but proved moſt Vain and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:137265:46"/> Corrupt, when they endeavoured to be moſt Exact.</p>
                     <p>So that we may Conclude with the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.10,11. &amp;c. <hi>Finally my Brethren, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might; put on the whole Armour of God, that ye may be able to ſtand againſt all the Wiles of the Devil; For we wreſtle not with Fleſh and Blood,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We obſerve hence, <hi>The growth, increaſe, and Final Victory of True Grace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Againſt Hope he believed in Hope.</hi> Math. 13.32. <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is compared to a Grain, and to Leaven that leaveneth the whole Lump.</hi> Grace is of a ſpreading nature, it ſwells it ſelf into the whole man, and makes the Soul riſe as high as Heaven. Grace lies not in the Heart, as a Stone in the Earth, but puts it ſelf forth in vigorous Actings. To this refers that exhortation, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Fall not from your Stedfaſtneſs, but grow in Grace,</hi> &amp;c. The firſt appearance of it on the Soul, may be but as the Wings of the Morning, ſpreading themſelves upon the Mountains, yet it is ſtill ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing higher and higher upon it, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:137265:46"/> away all filthy Miſts and Vapours of Sin, till it arrive to its Meridian height; ſuch is the ſtrength and force of Divinity in it. Though at firſt, when it enters on the Soul, it may ſeem to be ſowen in weakneſs, yet it ſtill raiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h it ſelf in Power: As Chriſt was in his <hi>Bodily</hi> appearance, ſtill increaſing in Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dom and Knowledg, and Favour with God and Man, till he was perfected with Glory; ſo is he alſo in his Gracious Appearance in his Saints, who ſhall go from ſtrength to ſtrength, till they appear before God in <hi>Sion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Reaſons hereof are taken,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. From the Principle or Fountain whence Grace Floweth; And that is, Chriſt and his Spirit; of Infinite Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and irreſiſtable Efficacy; ſo that unleſs Chriſt be overcome, Grace cannot be overcome. Grace being a Creature, is in its own nature pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing (for ours is no better Coin than <hi>Adams</hi>) but in Chriſts Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it can never periſh. The Saints Graces of themſelves, like Glaſs, may break, but being held in the Hand of Chriſt, they can never be broken; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>We are kept by
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:137265:47"/> the Power of God through Faish unto Salvation.</hi> The ſmall Muſtard-Seed ſhall not be killed, the little Spark of Fire ſhall not be quenched; there is an overflowing Power to draw them forth and perfect them. Where-ever the frame of Grace is begun, it ſhall be brought forth to a compleatneſs, and Chriſts Kingdom in that Soul ſhall be victorious over all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Corruption.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. From the Nature of the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Grace: They are finite, and mortally Wounded. Our Lord led <hi>Captivity Captive,</hi> Heb. 2.14. <hi>And through Death hath Deſtroyed him who hath the Power of Death.</hi> So that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerious Conſideration, I may ſay to all the Faithful, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſometime ſpake, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.16. <hi>Fear not, for they that are with you are more than they with them.</hi> Though inward Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and outward Enemies be Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and ſtrong, yet they ſhall not Finally proſper. Where Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes his Kingdom, it is ſo eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the <hi>Gates of Hell</hi> ſhall not prevail againſt it. Aſſaulted it may be, but Conquered it can never be. As it is ſaid of the old <hi>Romans,</hi> they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:137265:47"/> loſt ſome Battels, but never loſt a war. Chriſtians may have ſome Foils, but they ſhall be finally Victorious.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1.</label> In the Application here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I ſhall endeavour a little further to Diſcover the Nature of this Grace of <hi>Hope,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. By way of <hi>Information;</hi> the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry will be,</p>
                     <p>Firſt, <hi>What it is?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> It is a Divine Vertue, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed by the Spirit into the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and Wills of Actual Members of the Militant Church, whereby they certainly and patiently wait for thoſe good things God hath promiſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24,25. <hi>We are ſaved by Hope; but Hope that is ſeen is no Hope; for what a man ſees, why doth he yet hope for? but if we hope for that we ſee not, then we do with Patience wait for it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In which Deſcription we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt or Implyed, four things:</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Principal Author, <hi>The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God;</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his Abundant mercy hath Begotten us again unto a lively Hope, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:137265:48"/>
                     <p n="2">2. The <hi>Subject</hi> incluſive; partly the Underſtanding, partly the Will; the one Informed, the other perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to expect.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The <hi>Object</hi> about which it is Imployed; either <hi>Formal;</hi> which is God alone; his Power, Truth and Help to obtain the promiſed Good: or <hi>Material;</hi> and that is <hi>Glory,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered three wayes, <hi>viz. First,</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> which is Grace, and is the Object of Hope, either in the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives,</hi> whilſt the Lord is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Subject for Grace; Or, in Regard of a <hi>Fuller</hi> Meaſure of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees thereof; it not being with the Trees of Righteouſneſs, as it was with the Trees of Paradiſe, made perfect at once. <hi>Secondly</hi> of the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> and ſo all the good things that a member of the Church Militant is capable of, are a Secondary Object of Hope. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of both, which is perfect Beatitude in the Heavenly Kingdom; as the end whereunto all other means lead the Elect.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The Conditions of this Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Object, which <hi>Aquinas</hi> deſcribes to be,</p>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:137265:48"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Good;</hi> Hope looks at ſome good; ſo it differs from Fear, whichlooks at Evil.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Future Good;</hi> ſo that the Saints in Heaven, have no need nor uſe of it: their Expectation is drowned in Fruition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Difficult,</hi> Hope looks on, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders upon one ſide Pearls, which yet are in the ſhell; and on the other ſide Roſes; which yet it may enjoy with ſome Labour.</p>
                     <p>Such was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Hope, that he ſhould be the Father of ſuch a Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, being as it were Dead; that he ſhould enjoy a Land flowing with Milk and Honey; yet he was to ſuffer Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and wait for it forty years. And Laſtly,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Poſſible;</hi> So there is no Hope in the Damned. It is in thoſe on this ſide the Grave, quickned by the Living Spirit of God. Though the things they hope for are hard to come by, yet they are poſſible, and this is like Cork to the Net, keeps the heart from ſinking into Diſpair; it being the Balm of all Grief, the Coffin of Fear, and Cradle of Patience.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>What are oppoſites of this Grace?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:137265:49"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Two, 1. <hi>Preſumption;</hi> the Unbeliever hopes without ground, and will be invincibly followed by an ill ſucceſs of his pretenſions. The Rayes of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Hope were groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on a good Title; but men of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Stamp act otherwiſe; their Hope is an Impoſture, a Golden Dream. Like a dying mans Will, that hath neither Seal nor Witneſs to it: Therein he bequeaths ſuch and ſuch Lands and Legacies to one and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: but the Will being thus left naked, it ſignifies little: Such is the hope of a wicked man; it promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him great matters, that all in the Covenant of Grace is his, Chriſt and Heaven; but alas, all is a meer Deluſion, a Preſumption of his own Heart.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Deſpair;</hi> not <hi>Legal,</hi> which was in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and others; But <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical,</hi> notwithſtanding all ground of Hope. So <hi>Abraham</hi> did not: <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair</hi> looks on things through black Spectacles, and gives all for loſt; <hi>Hope</hi> doth the contrary.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Q</label> 
                        <hi>How is it poſſible to hope againſt Hope?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> 1. Becauſe of the Power of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:137265:49"/> Chriſt, upon which the Soul doth in great Straits, rowl it ſelf. Whatever Lets and Impediments do ariſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Promiſe and the fulfilling of it; though they be as high as Mountains, and as the Gates of Hell, yet the Believer can by Faith look upon them all but as Difficulties which cannot check the Power of Chriſt, but only Magnifie it. For, as jealous Thoughts of the Divine Arm, or fear that it may be encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with ſome inſuperable oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, makes the Hope of Promiſed Good, to be weak and uncertain, ſo the faithful and ſerious conſideration of Gods Power, a reſting upon it, produceth <hi>Hope againſt Hope,</hi> it turns every <hi>Valley of Achor</hi> into a door of Hope, adminiſters Manna in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and draws water out of the Rock, brings light out of darkneſs, comfort out of every Tryal. Thus <hi>Miconius</hi> wrote to <hi>Calvin</hi> upon view of the Churches Enemies, reflecting upon the Power of Chriſt; <hi>Gaudeo quod Chriſtus Dominus eſt, alioquin totus Deſperaſſem.</hi> I am Glad that Chriſt Reigns, otherwiſe I ſhould ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſpair. So the Believer in the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:137265:50"/> midſt of Straits, rejoyceth in the Power of Chriſt, who lives and Reigns for ever and ever!</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Spirit of Chriſt inwardly works and nouriſheth ſome Sparks of Hope always in the Hearts of his people. Thus it was with <hi>Job, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Paul,</hi> and a vaſt number of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faithful Souls, who ſparkling with the lightning Rays of Hope, have lift up their Palms in the midſt of Hazzards, and Gain'd Heaven by Violence, ſtill laying the degrees of their Honour in the depth of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering. This, like an Anchor, holds the Ship of the Soul in her greateſt Storms, and like an Helmet keeps off the Blows of the Sword or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows from entring, 1 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Let us who are of the day, be ſober, putting on the Breaſt-Plate of Faith and Love, and for an Helmet the Hope of Salvation.</hi> In time of publick Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, the Righteous have Hope. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16. <hi>The Lord will roar out of</hi> Zion, <hi>the Heaven and Earth ſhall ſhake, but the Lord will be the Hope of his People.</hi> So that if all outward hope be taken away, their hope in God is not taken away. Upon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:137265:50"/> this account it was, that the Jews being Priſoners in <hi>Babylon,</hi> are called <hi>Priſoners of Hope, Zech.</hi> 9.10. If Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth be ready to come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet through the ſtrength of the Divine Spirit working in their Hearts, Believers have <hi>Hope;</hi> which as a Bow in the Heavens all furniſhed with Emeralds, never loſeth it force.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Their former Experiences are a Foundation of Hope againſt Hope. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.4. — <hi>And Experience, Hope.</hi> Hoſ. 2.5. <hi>I will give the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Achor for a door of Hope.</hi> This Valley of <hi>Achor</hi> (ſo called from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans</hi> Sacriledge, to deter men from Sin,) ſome think to be the ſame with <hi>Engeddi,</hi> mentioned ſo often in the <hi>Canticles;</hi> however, both are neer to <hi>Jericho,</hi> and in it, they taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the firſt Fruits of <hi>Canaan,</hi> as an earneſt of the reſt: in it they ſaw abundance of Plenty, and were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted and Refreſhed therewith: all that the Lord did then for his People, and now ſaith, he will give it to the Church, <hi>for a door of Hope.</hi> A Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever brings in a Catalogue of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.65. <hi>Thou haſt dealt well with thy Servant!</hi> In how
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:137265:51"/> many Caſes hath he had Experience of God? when Sin and Temptation have been ſtrong, he hath come in with Auxiliary Forces, and his Grace hath proved ſufficient. When the poor Soul hath been even ſinking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Fear, God hath recovered him out of the Quick-Sands, and lifted his head above the deep Water. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>O Lord thou art my Glory and the lifter up of my Head:</hi> When <hi>David</hi> was in the Mouth of Danger, the Lord delivered him. <hi>I was pluckt out of the Mouth</hi> of the <hi>Lyon;</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> The Believer hath many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences and theſe beget Hope. <hi>Thou haſt and wilt Deliver,</hi> ſaith Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <hi>David.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. By looking on things, not as they are at preſent, or in their own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but as they ſhall be by the Lords promiſe. Surely ſaith the poor Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, <hi>He is faithful that hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:</hi> As he is able to fulfil the leaſt <hi>Iota,</hi> of whatever he hath ſpoken, ſo he is infallible in what he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. As no impediment can ariſe to hinder his Power, ſo no contingency can fall out to alter his Will; all his Promiſes being in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>yea and Amen,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:137265:51"/>
                     <p>Theſe and ſuch like Meditations ſerve to uphold and keep Believers from being injurious to God, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to believe <hi>in Hope againſt Hope.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</label> This Doctrine adminiſters incomparable Comfort; whoſoever is Chriſts, is enabled to believe in <hi>Hope againſt Hope.</hi> When Comfort can neither be ſeen, felt nor appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, when Fears and Diſtreſſes are on every ſide, and all hope of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is taken away, when nature affords no ground of Hope, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to expect the fulfilling of a Promiſe, but ſuggeſting many poſing arguments to impede and gainſay the Truths of it, and to make Faith as feeble as their Bodies, when old and Crazy; then to <hi>hope againſt Hope.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the Church ſhall be raiſed and preſerved from ſo many Enemies, is <hi>againſt Hope.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. <hi>O our God, wilt thou not judg us? for we have no Might against this great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that cometh againſt us, neither know we what to do, but our eyes are upon thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That a Wound ſhall be Healed;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:137265:52"/> It is againſt Hope. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. <hi>A Wounded Spirit who can bear?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. That many and ſtrong Luſts ſhall be vanquiſhed and ſubdued; <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>O Wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me, from this Body of Sin and Death!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. That an impure Soul ſhall be prepared for and received into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; it is againſt hope; yet ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Come let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord, though your Sins be as Red as Crimſon, I will make them white as Snow. — To day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradice.</hi> Oh, ſtrive for this Heavenly Hope.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Q.</label> 
                        <hi>How may it be Attained?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>A.</label> As other Graces are wrought, ſo is this. It is the work of God; wherefore he is called, <hi>The God of all Grace,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10. He is the firſt Planter, the Promoter and Finiſher of Grace. God is called the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> and he muſt light up this Candle in your Souls.</p>
                     <p>More particularly, it is obtained, 1. By <hi>Experience, Rom.</hi> 5.4. as <hi>David</hi> argued, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.37. And Holy <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. Experience breeds Confidence. Thou <hi>haſt,</hi> thou <hi>ſhalt,</hi>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:137265:52"/> is the ordinary argument uſed by the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi> And ſo the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted her ſelf, and Nouriſheth her Hope, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.21,24. <hi>This I Recalled to mind, therefore I hope in thee.</hi> And, <hi>The Lord is my Portion, ſaith my Soul, therefore will I Hope in him.</hi> The obſervation of Gods Merciful Acts of Providence to his Church in general, as to any of his People in particular, is the way to kindle Hope. 2. By <hi>Patience</hi> and Comfort of the Scriptures. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. As the Blood and Spirits are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by the Veins and Arteries, ſo is the Spirit of God by the Word and Promiſe, helping the Soul to lay hold on <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> which is a Grace, as of Union, ſo of Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Q.</label> 
                        <hi>How may it be known where it is?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> 1. By the Object thereof, God in Chriſt, things Above; not Means, not Creatures, principally or Terminatively. A man of ſuch hope, dares not pluck off the Crown from the head of Free Grace, or ſnatch it out of the hand of Divine Power, to ſet it on the head of any Creature; But he makes God his hope. Thus is <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith deſcribed.</p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:137265:53"/>
                     <p n="2">2. By the manner of working. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it begets a Care and Love to Purity. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. <hi>He that hath this Hope, Purifieth himſelf even as he is Pure.</hi> As Lightning is to the Air, ſuch is Hope to the Soul; It purifieth the Soul, after an high Strain, <hi>even as God is pure; Secundum ſpeciem,</hi> though not <hi>ad gradum;</hi> i. e. In kind and Quality; though not in Act, yet in deſire and affection. Hope purgeth the Conſcience <hi>from dead works, to ſerve the Living and True God.</hi> By it the Soul draws nigh to <hi>God,</hi> and comes to have a ſight and view of him, and is thereby aſſimulated to him. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to our Faith, ſo is our Holineſs, and according to our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations will be our Converſations. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It quickens to Duty, is a Whetſtone to Induſtry. It is Hope that carries the Ship to Sea, and ploughs the Curled Ocean: It is Hope that weilds the Souldiers Weapon, and ſteels his Helmet: It is Hope that feeds the Sower, even when he ſeems to caſt away his Seed; very Tears are dropt in hope; and ſo Mournful Souls are led along the milky way, to the Eternal Father. Hope teacheth
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:137265:53"/> men to caſt Bread upon the waters, where it may be fed and afterward reſtored. Thus Divine Hope is active in its influence, is as Wind to the Sails, Wheels to the Chariot, and wings to the Bird; It makes active in Religion, <hi>To Run the way of Gods Commandments,</hi> and never ceaſeth, till its object be obtained. The Furnace ſhall not terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a mans hope in Chriſt: As fire, it is ſparkling and Flaming: Though the Winds blow, the Rain fall and Rage, yet <hi>Hope</hi> ſeated in the Heart of a Believer, as on a Rock, grows <hi>up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hope,</hi> and ſo perſeveres in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, till Charity, that circling endleſs thing, hath perfected its wings to make its Flight to the Eternal Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Repoſe, paſſing the Vail into the Tabernacle of the Sanctuary, where <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> the Forerunner hath made his Entry, for the Salvation of his Faithful Ones.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Glory be to God in the Higheſt!</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:54"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:54"/>
                  <p>The Juſtice of GOD ASSERTED, IN Seeming Contrariant <hi rend="blackletterType">Providences:</hi> And Vindicated from the Cavils of Corrupt Men under them.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 145.17.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Lord is holy in all his ways, and righteous in all his works.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Rev. 153.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Juſt and true are thy ways, thou King of Saints.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Alſop,</hi> at the Angel and Bible in the <hi>Poultrey;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>James Cowſey,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Exeter.</hi> 1682.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:137265:55"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137265:55"/>
                  <head>THE JUSTICE of GOD ASSERTED, In Seeming Contrariant PROVIDENCES.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Job 34.17.</bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>— Wilt thou Condemn him that is moſt juſt?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JOB</hi>'s Great Afflictions make a great noiſe in the world; they Sounded ſo far, as his Friends at a great Diſtance from him, hear of them; whether by the Miniſtry of good or bad Angels, or of neither, it Skills not. Ill News is ſwift of Foot, ſaith the Greek Proverb <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and like ill weather, which comes ere it be ſent for. <hi>The Sins and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137265:56"/> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſcries of Good People are much talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, and ſoon bruited abroad.</hi> This brings <hi>Jobs</hi> Friends out of a Deſire and Deſign to Condole with and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, (the Character of true Friendſhip, which is ſuited to a day of Adverſity,) though it fell out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; for they tormented him, well nigh as much as Satan himſelf, though it were of Ignorance and Unwitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rather than of ill will or fore-thought Malice. <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the <hi>Tema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, Bildad</hi> the <hi>Shuhite,</hi> and <hi>Zophar</hi> the <hi>Naamathite;</hi> all likely <hi>Idume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and men much eſteemed for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Godlineſs; as is manifeſt in their ſeveral Diſputations and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes: in which they admoniſh him to Repent; aſſuring him, that he could be no leſs than a groſs Sinner, and Hypocrite, becauſe ſo grievouſly Afflicted, (a great Miſtake in them; and uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lly the Reproach of the world upon the Gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ion of the Juſt.) To Anſwer this, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ob</hi> now Addreſſeth himſelf, though Tormented in Body, Perpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xed in Mind, ſtoutly defending his own Inno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> y, and ſeeming to Tax the Lord; as Dogs in a Chain Bark at their own Maſters. To this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137265:56"/> his Friends make a ſharp Reply, from the 15th <hi>Chap. to the</hi> 22. and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth them again with greater Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Boldneſs than before. Whereupon they begin a ſecond Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and the Diſcourſe Continues, till the Parties grew weary of <hi>Job;</hi> who ſhewed himſelf a Valiant and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Champion: only as every Pomegranate hath ſome rotten Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels in it, ſo <hi>Job</hi> had his Frailties and out-burſts, Cauſed by Extremity of Pain and Exceſs of Paſſion; and who amongſt the beſt Spirits, in Strange and Heavy Accidents, do not pay ſome Tribute to the Natural Paſſions of Men? Theſe Ending, <hi>Elihu,</hi> a ſtander by, a good Man, ſteps in, as being all in a Flame, undertakes to carry on the work againſt and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth <hi>Jobs</hi> Speeches, <hi>Chap.</hi> 32. but not ſo candidly, and refelleth them, but not ſo mildly, as was meet. True it was, <hi>Job</hi> in his Heat, had let fall many Laviſh Speeches, but yet it was far from him to ſay, either that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was without Sin, or that God was unjuſt, as <hi>Elihu</hi> would bear him down; very unfitly taking ſome ſayings of his, that way Sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137265:57"/> Whence may be Noted by the way,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Words prove not alway what they Intend, but as they are Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words of the beſt men are not free from ſtraining: they would yield Milk, when they are forced to yield Blood: Inferences may be made upon what we ſay or do, ſuch as we never thought of. <hi>Arbitror nonnullus in quibuſdam Locis Librorum meorum Opinaturos me Senſiſſe quod non Senſi; aut non Senſiſſe quod Senſi;</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Trinitat. ad Finem;</hi> and it fell out accordingly; for as <hi>Baronius</hi> Witneſſeth, after <hi>Auſtins</hi> Death, aroſe up divers, <hi>qui ex ejus Scriptis male Perceptis, Complures In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vexerunt Errores;</hi> who out of his Writings wreſted and miſconſtructed, brought in many Errors, which they endeavoured to maintain, by the name and Authority of Saint <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> And the like may be ſaid of <hi>Luther.</hi> Which may teach us to ſet a Watch over the Door of our Lips; to Weigh our Words in Ballance, to Utter few and Seaſonable Words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elihu,</hi> we ſee heated, a Fire is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137265:57"/> kindled on the Hearth of his Heart, by the Spirit of Judgment and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſuch as many Waters cannot Quench; Wherein, though <hi>Elihu</hi> was ſomewhat Faulty, yet becauſe he was right in the main, all was taken well. Noting,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How apt even good men are to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Sin with their beſt Actions; To Plow with an Ox and an Aſs;</hi> but the Lord is pleaſed to Conſider whereof we are made, and Graciouſly to lay the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Mercy on the Scars of our Sins; as that Limner in the Story. He looks over what is his, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looks what is ours. Where there are no Sins of Allowance in us, there ſhall be Grains of Allowance to us: he will not caſt away his Pearls for every Speck of Dirt.</p>
                  <p>The Ground of <hi>Elihu</hi>'s Anger and Heightned Zeal is mentioned <hi>Chap.</hi> 32. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>becauſe Job juſtified himſelf rather than God.</hi> This he did not directly and in ſo many words, but by a ſeeming Conſequence, and <hi>Elihu</hi> was kindled at it. It is a Bleſſed thing to have a Stomach for God, to be blown up in his Cauſe; as were <hi>Moſes Elijah, Phineas, David,</hi> Chriſt, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137265:58"/> the Angel of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> to be all on a Light Fire with Love to God, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt all that doth him any Diſhonour. All true Zeal is of a Maſculine Spirit. <hi>Job</hi> had utter'd ſome Diſcontented Speeches againſt God, which Reflected on his Honour and Juſtice; he had deſpaired of a Reſtauration, and moſt earneſtly wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Death, and thereby ſeemed to Juſtify himſelf rather than God, and this <hi>Elihu</hi> could not brook; and therefore Continues his ſharp Rebuke, in this Chapter, to the humbling of <hi>Job,</hi> and Vindicating of God. <hi>Job</hi> was not ſo Righteous, but that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this Affliction; as there may be Cauſe in the very beſt, as well by Reaſon of their Actual Prevarications as of their Birth-Sin. <hi>God cannot do Wrong.</hi> It is Inconſiſtent, 1. With his Nature, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Far be it from God to do Wickedneſs.</hi> He cannot Sin. In which Senſe only it is ſaid, he <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> do this or that; not through Want, but through Height and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Power. <hi>He cannot do Wickedly,</hi> becauſe he is Omnipotent. It is for poor Creatures to be Lyable to ſuch Imperfections; the Divine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137265:58"/> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> cannot be a Principle of <hi>Dir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ction,</hi> and the Divine <hi>Will</hi> cannot be a Principle of <hi>Injunction,</hi> and therefore the Divine <hi>Powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> cannot therein ſhew it ſelf to be a Principle of Execution. 2. It appears from his Actions, <hi>Ver.</hi> 11. He is ſo far from doing Wrong to any, that every man <hi>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll find according to his way.</hi> And although this is not done forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, yet we may write upon it, and Reckon, that, <hi>Non dum Omnium di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erum ſoles Occiderunt;</hi> as ſure as the Night follows the Day, Account will come, and God will Reward unto each man according to his Works. His Providence, like a well-drawn Picture that Eyeth every one in the Room, obſerveth all things. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though one Man may not know ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor any man know himſelf, yet God, following as it were all men hard at the Heels, doth with his eyes narrowly obſerve and mark what way every man Wolks in, he ſeeth all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oings. And let none pleaſe themſelves in their Sinful Practices, as if God did not ſee them, becauſe for a time they eſcape unpuniſhed: for Sin and Puniſhment are tied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137265:59"/> with Chains of Adamant, and cannot be long aſunder. 3. His <hi>Will</hi> doth evince it; <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>God will not do wickedly.</hi> He can do whatever he will do: but he cannot do Wickedly becauſe, for want of good in Sin, it cannot become the Object of his <hi>Will. Job</hi> had ſaid as much before, but then he ſeemingly daſht all again, with his Inconſiderate Complaints and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings; and this <hi>Eliſha</hi> could not bear, but again and again Celebrates the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God.</p>
                  <p>This whole Chapter is a Golden Flood of Grave Diſcourſe; an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legant Oration; if we Conſider the matter or the manner; It is a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond ſet in Gold. Each line in its place, is adorn'd with the Enamel of Divine Affection, which breathes through the Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>Here, as in a Mirrour, is the Lords Righteouſneſs preſented; his Juſtice is diſplayed in moſt orient Colours. And when <hi>Elihu</hi> hath done all he can, he ſeems to ſay, as <hi>Cicero</hi> once did of <hi>Craſſus</hi> and <hi>Antonius,</hi> Roman O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, If any man thought he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken too much in Commendation of them, he muſt needs be ſuch a one,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137265:59"/> as either knew them not, or was not able to judge of their worth.</p>
                  <p>The Text is one ſingle demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Juſtice, carried on in an excellent Metaphor: taken from binding up the Wounded, after the manner of Chirurgeons: And then the words are tranſlated by ſome thus; <hi>An qui odit juſtitiam, Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos imitaretur?</hi> Would he that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Righteouſneſs, do as Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſe to do? Would God, if He were Unrighteous, bind up the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-Hearted, or receive into favour, as he doth, a Sinner that Repenteth, doing him good again, as if there had never been any breach between them? It is noted, that a <hi>King</hi> hath his name in the Greek Tongue from <hi>healing,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ab</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Medela;</hi> and that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.7. <hi>A Governour</hi> is called <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> or Binder up; its the ſame word here in the Text. But how unfit for ſuch an Office, muſt he needs be, who doth not only, not do Right, but hates it? As did <hi>Nero, Caligula, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus</hi> and others, enemies of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</p>
                  <p>— <hi>And wilt thou Condemn him that is moſt Juſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:137265:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:137265:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:137265:61"/>
                  <p>None in his right Wits will do ſo. This were for man to exalt himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Divine Majeſty, and for the dribling River to vye with the Drowning Ocean. And yet what do they leſs then this, who grudg at Gods proceedings, and are ready to think, if they had the ordering of things in their own hands, they could diſpoſe of them a fair deal better? As <hi>Alphonſe King</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> the Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of whoſe name is marr'd with the dead flie of his Atheiſtical Speech, <hi>That if he had been in Gods ſtead, he would have diſpoſed the World better than it is.</hi> Chriſtians beholding the Lords ſeverer Diſpenſations againſt them, their budding Flowers opened in a warm day, ſhut again in a Cold one, and their flowing Tides to become ebbing Waters; God cloathed as it were with darkneſs, and they not able to cleave the Clouds to behold him walking on the Vault of his Palace, nor trace him in his beamy walk through the midſt of the Sanctuary, among theſe <hi>Golden Candleſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cks</hi> which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve long ſuffered a dimneſs; are apt to conceive that the Lord deals not well with them, and they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137265:61"/> deſerve better from him, God might have been a wiſer and a better God. Blaſphemy is the fruit of Diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let none charge God fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Text will teach us to be better Commentators upon Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>viz.</hi> Even to <hi>juſtifie God in all his ſayings,</hi> and to give him glory in all his doings, by our ſilence or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Summa totalis,</hi> or ſenſe of all, falls into this entire propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whatever mens apprehenſions are, God in all the ways of bis Providence towards the whole World, is a most juſt God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God is moſt juſt.</hi> A univerſal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. So he was, thus he is, and ſo ever ſhall be: The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhall be diſſolved into nothing, and men as they are, into Falſities; But God will be found <hi>juſt</hi> for ever.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall firſt endeavour to explain this truth, and afterwards confirm it.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Explication,</hi> know, that one may be ſaid to be <hi>juſt</hi> three ways,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Obedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ia Activa,</hi> by Active Obedience, and that Voluntary and Perfect; both <hi>extenſively,</hi> in Regard
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137265:62"/> of the <hi>Object;</hi> and <hi>Intenſively,</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>Suhject;</hi> So, Chriſt alone is ſaid to be juſt here; his Heart and the Law were Uniſons; anſwering each other as Face anſwereth Face in a Glaſs. And the Saints ſhall be hereafter; when the Imperfect Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Grace in the Soul, ſhall by the Penſil of the Holy Ghoſt, be drawn forth in their orient Beauty, and the Vermilion of Glory be laid upon them.</p>
                  <p>If it be Objected, <hi>That the Saints are ſaid to be juſt here?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, true. <hi>Joſeph</hi> is called a <hi>just man, Math.</hi> 1.19. ſo were <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Luke 1.16. ſaid <hi>to be Righteous before God,</hi> &amp;c. But to be underſtood,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Not <hi>Legall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> for Righteouſneſs of <hi>Creation,</hi> whereby God made man after his own Image, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, to walk exactly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of Juſtice. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man was then, though mutable, becauſe hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Holineſs depended upon and flowed from a Principl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lf, Original Juſtice; now loſt; and ſo, <hi>none is Righteous, no not one.</hi> But,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Evangellically,</hi> viz (1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>In De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderio
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137265:62"/> &amp; Conatu.</hi> The Saints do Level at the mark of Perfection. They hunger after compleat Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: whence it is ſaid, <hi>they Sin not, John</hi> 3.9. becauſe though they be not without Sin, yet their Wills is againſt Sin; they have voted it down. When they fail, they mourn; and this is called Goſpel-Righteouſneſs. (2) <hi>Comparative &amp; Reſpectu Impiorum;</hi> in Reſpect of the Wicked; and ſo <hi>Noah</hi> was ſaid to be <hi>perfect in his Generation;</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Compared with the Prophane World, was <hi>a Perfect, juſt man.</hi> Gold in the Oar, Compared with Lead or Braſs, is perfect; a field of Wheat may have ſome Thiſtles growing in it, yet Compared with that of Tares, is perfect Wheat. (3) <hi>Divina Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione.</hi> God doth accept of them in and through Chriſt, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Ye are compleat in him:</hi> Through the Red-glaſs every thing appears red; ſo through the Red glaſs of Chriſts Blood, the gracious Soul ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears lovely and Beautifull in Gods eye. They are <hi>accepted in the Belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Epheſ.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. One may be ſaid to be juſt,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137265:63"/> 
                     <hi>Gratia,</hi> by Grace; as the Elect and Called are <hi>juſt: Juſtitia unionis Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putata;</hi> by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Imputed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.6. This is as truely theirs to juſtify, as it is Chriſts to beſtow; and this is a Chriſtians Triumph, when he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed in himſelf, he is undefiled in his Head; in his Righteouſneſs the Saints ſhall ſhine brighter than the Angels. Or, <hi>Juſtitia communionis Inherente;</hi> viz. the Graces of Chriſts Spirit, Holineſs of Heart and Life; which <hi>Cajetan</hi> calleth <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Natura,</hi> by Nature, and ſo two wayes, 1. <hi>Dono,</hi> by Gift; as <hi>Adam</hi> was by Creation. His will (which is the Univerſal Appetite of the whole man) was Wonderfully good, Furniſhed with ſeveral Habits of Goodneſs, as the Firmament with Glittering Stars. There was in him a propenſion to all good; as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in Tune, he was full of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; like a Bright Air and a pure Beauty without the leaſt Cloud to ſtain it; his Heart was without the leaſt Tincture of Impurity; as Wine that hath no Sophiſtication. Such was <hi>Adams</hi> Holineſs. But this is not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137265:63"/> now to be found on Earth, we muſt go to Heaven for it. 2. <hi>Eſſentia,</hi> by Eſſence; and ſo God only is juſt. Righteouſneſs in God is as Beams in the Sun, Water in the Fountain, and Lines in the Centre, it is Original: he is the Pattern and Prototype of all Righteouſneſs; juſt <hi>ad intra,</hi> as he is; juſt <hi>ad extra,</hi> as he works; every way juſt.</p>
                  <p>Some may underſtand the firſt only, as <hi>Oſiander</hi> would every where; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the latter only: I conceive both may and muſt be here underſtood: God is juſt in <hi>himſelf,</hi> and in all his <hi>Miniſtrations</hi> to the Sons of men.</p>
                  <p>Again, He is ſaid to be juſt,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Qui juſta facit &amp; imperat juſte;</hi> So doth God, who never Acted or Commanded any thing, but what was in it ſelf equal and reaſonable; although perhaps to our ſhallow and corrupt Underſtanding it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear otherwiſe; as to our eyes, Turrets and Steeples, how upright, ſoever, if their height be exceeding great, do oftentimes ſeem crooked, and look as if they ſtood awry: But all Gracious Hearts diſcover that Beauty and Equity in all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137265:64"/> as draws forth their Aſſent and and Conſent to them; they can ſay, Bleſſed be God for his Precepts; <hi>His Commands are not Grievous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Qui opera quadrat adjuris Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta;</hi> So doth God, whoſe Will is the ſupream Reaſon; <hi>Nec Recta ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, ſed &amp; ipſa Regula;</hi> not only right, but the very Rule of Right; And im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it is for him to do wrong by erring from the Rule of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Men may overſlip themſelves, and miſcarry or deny Juſtice, in which caſe, Appeals have been made to God; as in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. The bold Counteſs of <hi>Arundel,</hi> Appeal'd from the King and his bad Counſellors, to the Court of Heaven. And in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Holy-War,</hi> Relation is given of a <hi>Templar,</hi> who being to be burnt at <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> at the place of Execution, he ſaw the <hi>Pope</hi> and King <hi>Philip</hi> looking out of a Window, and cryed to them, <hi>Clement</hi> thou Cruel Tyrant, ſeeing there is no higher a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Mortals to whom I ſhould Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal for my unjuſt death, I cite thee together with King <hi>Philip,</hi> before the Tribunal of Chriſt Jeſus, the Juſt Judg, who Redeemed me; there,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137265:64"/> both to appear within one year and a day, where I will lay open my Cauſe, and Juſtice ſhall be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect: And it fell out ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Qui promiſſa ſervat;</hi> So doth God: He is faithful <hi>that promiſed.</hi> One letter of his name, whereby he hath made himſelf known, is, <hi>Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in Truth;</hi> And Chriſt is called <hi>the faithful and true Witneſs;</hi> And the Counſels of God are ſaid to be <hi>Faithful and True.</hi> He ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in it, as he hath no mixture of the contrary; though the beſt of men have ſome; as for example; A precious Stone, hath ſome ſpeckling or cloud, but light it ſelf admits of none. God is light, and with him is no darkneſs at all; ſo God is true, and in him is no Falſhood at all. <hi>God that cannot lie hath promiſed,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Titus</hi> 2. God may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay his Promiſe, but he cannot deny his Promiſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Qui ſuum cuique tribuit, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia diſtributiva;</hi> So doth God; He gives to every man his own. It is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Tyranny to invade ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans Right: An Evil, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137265:65"/> cannot be imputed to God without Horrid Blaſphemy.</p>
                  <p>But to come nearer; we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider God under a fourfold notion, and in each ſhall find him <hi>Juſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Dominus,</hi> as Lord; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his purpoſe, touching man to be Created, of glorifying his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Juſtice, Wiſdom and Power; in Saving, Damning, calling effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, denying others; chuſing, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, reprobating; Where it is not ſafe to ſearch too far; <hi>Quod neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur ſine Crimine, ne diſcutietur cum diſcrimine;</hi> nor ſtrive to know with danger, what we may be ignorant of with ſafety; in ſuch things, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration is better Piety, than appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; (Curioſity is the firſt ſpawn of Sin) nor to judg that unjuſt, which Reaſon apprehends not. Of all his Decrees, we may conclude, <hi>There is no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs with God.</hi> Rom. 9.13. <hi>Jacob have I loved,</hi> &amp;c. Let not Carnal Reaſon dare to reprehend what it doth not apprehend. Let none forbid Faith to ſwim, where Reaſon cannot wade. Baniſh <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Blaſphemy, which will needs have a Reaſon of Divine Myſteries.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137265:65"/> Except they ſee, they will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; whereby Faith is become, as ſome of that ſort of men have made bold to call it, <hi>Theologorum Ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium, Scripturarum Tyrannidem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Creator,</hi> with reſpect to the Means of Execution. Giving being, permitting the fall, Ordaining and Governing by his Providence, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and diſpoſing both the good and bad. All theſe are juſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>The Lord reward him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Works.</hi> Math. 5.45. <hi>He maketh the Sun to ſhine on the Evil and Good.</hi> In which, he is at an Infinite Diſtance from Unrighteouſneſs: for in theſe he moves <hi>according to the Council of his own Will,</hi> and this is ever Rational; though our ſhallow Reaſon in this State of Degeneracy and Mortallity, be not able to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom the Depths of its Contrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and is thereupon ready to Cavil and Call in Queſtion their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Pator Electorum;</hi> by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Righteouſneſs, viz. <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in his Decrees, and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, two principal Emanations of the Divine Being, Reſpecting his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137265:66"/> Creatures, whom he hath taken into ſo neer a Relation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; all which he juſtifies, for and by the Obedience of his Son, who is Conſtituted by the Father to be the Head of all his Elect, to be his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and to be by him brought to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Bleſſedneſs. See 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>If we Confeſs our Sins, he is Faithfull to forgive.</hi> The word <hi>[Faithful]</hi> refers to Gods <hi>Promiſes,</hi> as <hi>[Just]</hi> doth to the <hi>Blood of Chriſt,</hi> the Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome received, whereby the Saints are Cleanſed; And it ſtands not with the Divine Juſtice to demand the Debt twice, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and the <hi>Debtor;</hi> but upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion he is <hi>Faithful and Juſt to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Judex,</hi> as a Judg, to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute Rewards according to Works; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. This is the exactneſs of that Divine Juſtice which Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs in God. The World is a great Book conſiſting of many Leaves and Pages; This Judg will peruſe every Leaf, Page, Line, and Tittle of it; and make the great <hi>Index expurgatorius,</hi> blot out the names of thouſands, take a funder
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137265:66"/> this whole Volumn, caſt much into the Fire, bind up the reſt as a perfect Volumn of elect ones for Eternity. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.7. all the World ſhall ſee their Judg, their Crimes, their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, Conſcience, and Satan, if out of Chriſt, or if believing in him, then <hi>Pardon</hi> ſealed with the Blood of the Judge, their <hi>Heaven</hi> ſmiling in his Smiles; <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.12.</p>
                  <p n="1">In three things he agrees with up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Judges, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. In Loving Juſtice and hating Iniquity. <hi>Job</hi> is ſaid, to have accounted <hi>Juſtice his Robe and Diadem.</hi> Chap. 29.14. and of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> that excellent Prince, that when he gave the Sword of Power, to any whom he made Governour of any Province, he uſed to ſay, <hi>Accipe hunc Gladium, ſi benefecero, utere pro me ſin aliter, contra me.</hi> It was from this Love of Juſtice. Of <hi>Fabricius</hi> a Senatour of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is recorded as his <hi>Encomium</hi> and left as his mark of Honour, that a man might as ſoon turn the Sun from its Courſe, as turn him out of the Courſe of Juſtice. From this very Principle it was, that <hi>Ariſtides</hi> obtained the Report of the <hi>Juſt</hi> from all in his time. Now if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137265:67"/> this be ſo true of men, how much more muſt it be true of God. <hi>The Right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ous Lord l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>veth Righteouſneſs. Pſal.</hi> 33.5. <hi>He Loveth Righteouſneſs and Judgment!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In Impartiality and Equality, hearing all ſides. <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that when he ſate in Judgment, he was wont <hi>alteram aurem prebere Actori, alteram vero integram ſervare reo,</hi> alway to ſtop one ear to the Plantiff, ſaying he kept that for the Defendant; one mans tale being good, till another be told. <hi>Aequum me utrique parti in Diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ptan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Controverſis quam Iutuenda Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciplina praebebo;</hi> ſaid <hi>Juſtinian;</hi> I will hear both Cauſes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this is a Rule obſerved by God; <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21. <hi>I will go down and ſee,</hi> &amp;c. Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken according to our <hi>Dialect,</hi> after the manner of a Judge, who firſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the Cauſe exactly, before he will give the Sentence. God doth not make the <hi>Sword</hi> the Judge; he Weighs things in the Ballance; he ever lyeth <hi>Judgment to the Line;</hi> When God is on a work of Juſtice he is not on a Riot, as if he cared, not whom he did hit, but goeth in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137265:67"/> Way of a Circuit, with the Offendor, <hi>I will go down and ſee!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. In paſſing Sentence without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons. The Juſt Judge fears no mans Condition in Judge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, he beholds not the faces of any perſons, but the Cauſe; Like <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> he is without Pedigree, This <hi>Son of Righteouſneſs</hi> ſhines on Beggars as well as on the Nobles. <hi>Job</hi> 34.19. <hi>God accepts of no mans Perſon;</hi> No not the Perſons of Princes; <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.23. Kings and Nobles muſt come to his Bar, and receive Sentence, as well as poor, Inferiour Perſons. He will do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon men, be they what they will be. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.24.</p>
                  <p>But in three things, he ſurpaſſeth all, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In <hi>Authority,</hi> which is derived to him from none. He is Lord Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount and hath <hi>Poteſtatem</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and extends to all. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. He hath <hi>Jus Imperii,</hi> and <hi>Jus Dominii;</hi> which none can have, but ſubordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; derivatively from him: His King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom ruleth over all. His Name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on his Thigh, is <hi>King of Kings.</hi> As among men, it is one of the <hi>Jura
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:137265:68"/> Regalia,</hi> the Flowers of the Crown to enact Laws and Statutes; it is much more true of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In <hi>Liberty:</hi> He is not tied to Law, in reſpect of time manner or meaſure. The greateſt and beſt Judges on Earth, do or ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern by Law, to the making of which others concur as well as they; But God is a Law to himſelf. He and none but he can write on his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Edicts, <hi>Stat per ratione voluntas,</hi> My Will is my Law, (which is Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in God, but Tyranny in man) his Will becauſe of the Holineſs of his Nature, is always juſt. He can better ſay than ever <hi>Conſtantine</hi> that <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperour could, <hi>Quod ego volo, pro Canone ſit;</hi> Let my Will be your Soveraign Rule; ſith things are Right becauſe I will them, I will not becauſe they are Right.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fallibility.</hi> He cannot err in deciding Controverſies and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; being Omniſcient, nothing is hid from him, but all things are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed to his eye. He is never at a ſtand. No ignorance dwells in his Underſtanding. Fair Shews can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver delude him; Colourable and Falſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137265:68"/> Reports cannot miſlead him, as Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Judges may be. He can never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit any, who is in truth faulty or inwardly unſound, nor upon any falſe ſuggeſtions paſs Cenſure upon any. He proceeds only upon certainty. Let the Papiſts conclude the Pope or his general Council infallible and ſo fit to decide Controverſies in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion; but we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all Mortals are more or leſs ſubject to Error and Uncertainty. If <hi>Moſes, Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> were among the beſt Magiſtrates, Prieſts or Prophets that ever were; they could not ſatisfie in all things, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome Unrighteouſneſs would be in them, or they, though innocent, will be juſtly accounted ſuſpitious.</p>
                  <p>Thus much only for Explication of the Doctrine;</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Confirmation</hi> thereof I am now to addreſs my ſelf: Which I do not intend to make as the Cords of a Tent ſtretched out to their utmoſt length, or unneceſſarily to enlarge, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did with Affectation their Phylacteries; yet for the more full eſtabliſhing thereof, it will he perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to ſpeak unto three things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:137265:69"/> to prove it by <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and to clear it from <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, for <hi>Authority;</hi> which though ſome do impiouſly Queſtion, yet to us it is ſufficiently and Invincibly bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And this the Scripture doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Affirmatively;</hi> when it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth God to be Juſt, Holy, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous (<hi>Exod.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.1.) all ſparkling Jewels of the Crown of Heaven, with which it flouriſheth; and which, however diverſified in our Conceptions, are notwithſtanding Identified with Gods eſſence, which is but one, though to us they appear to be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from each other, and all from it; as the vaſt Ocean, though but one, receives divers names from the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhoars it waſheth on; ſo how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Juſtice, Holineſs, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, be ſeveral Names Suited to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Operations, yet all are but one Simple Act in God, under thoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Denominations.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Negatively;</hi> when it removes all Injuſtice and Iniquity from him; (<hi>Deutr.</hi> 32.4.10.17. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.14.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:137265:69"/> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.14.) Righteouſneſs is the Embroidered Robe wherewith God is Cloathed. It is the Glory of the Godhead. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. <hi>Glorious in Holineſs,</hi> is his Name. Darkneſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Imputed to the Sun; no more can Sin to God. You may as ſoon Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate weight from Lead, or heat from Fire, as <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> from the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Affectively,</hi> When it Attributes to God, the Affection of Zeal, Anger, Fury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5.32.10. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.20. which are not in God ſuch Paſſions as they be in men; but an act of immutable Juſtice, and are not to be underſtood <hi>ſecundum Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbationis affectum,</hi> but <hi>ſecundum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is Effectum.</hi> Anger and Wrath in God, is nothing but <hi>Tranquilla Conſtitutio juſti Supplicii;</hi> a Calm and quiet Appointment of juſt Puniſhment, revenging Juſtice. And the ſame Juſtice of God, as it ſimply burns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin, is in Scripture called his <hi>Anger;</hi> when it doth more fiercely <hi>ex candeſcere</hi> or ſparkle out, it is called his <hi>Wrath.</hi> The ſame <hi>Juſtice</hi> when it pronounceth Sentence, is called his <hi>Judgment;</hi> when it is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:137265:70"/> brought to Execution, it is called his Vengeance: all directed againſt Evil.</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee the Truth to have an Innate Proof, ſhining with its own Beams: and by this, it ſhould prevail over mens Minds, vanquiſh unbelief and chaſe away the Clouds of Error. But,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, For <hi>Argument.</hi> Though the Scripture like the Sun-beams, are their own Diſcovery, yet one may contract them into three Glaſſes, wherein we may take a clearer View of them, and perceive a warmer Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from them falling on our Minds and Hearts. The Arguments grounded on the former Authority are theſe following, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. God is <hi>Agens liberrimum,</hi> a Debtor to none, bound to no Law, becauſe none was ever given to him, therefore he cannot offend in diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive Juſtice. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.15. <hi>Is it not lawful for me to do with my own as I will.</hi> Rom. 9.21. <hi>Hath not the Potter power over the Clay, to make one Veſſel to Honour and another to Diſhonour;</hi> i. e. He may lawfully, he hath full Authority ſo to do:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:137265:70"/> That's the meaning, and ſo runs that expreſſion in the Hebrew Text. <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.16. <hi>Cannot I do as this Potter;</hi> And <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.14. <hi>We cannot do this thing,</hi> i. e. We may not do it; It is unmeet, unlawful for us to do. Now this God can do, it is lawful, by Right he may. However by this awarding <hi>Paribus imparia,</hi> unlike proportions to men of like Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, conſidered in the ſame Lump and doing this arrbitrarily, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the good Pleaſure and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his own Will, ſets men a crying out of Iniquity in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; yet it is without reaſon and with great Injuſtice, for God is free; and beſides, his Will is the ſupream Rule of Righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He is <hi>Fons Justitia,</hi> Juſtice it ſelf, the original of Righteouſneſs, and it is impoſſible for him to do, or be the Author of Sin. Out of this Fountain cannot proceed ſweet Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and bitter; no more than white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs can black the Wall, or heat make one cold. Every thing is juſt, becauſe God doth it. He cannot do that which is contrary to his Nature. He cannot Lie, becauſe he is Truth it ſelf. God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:137265:71"/> canot Sin, becauſe he is perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He is <hi>Judex Mundi,</hi> as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham ſaid,</hi> Gen. 18.25. <hi>And ſhall not the Judge of the World do R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght?</hi> It is <hi>Abrahams</hi> acknowledgment of God in Covenant. He adem the World and ſhall judge the World. Theſe are atributed to him interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, <hi>to make and judge the World,</hi> And he certainly will do Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. We may as eaſily ſuppoſe God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ceaſe from being Judge of the World, as ceaſe to do Right. He i the Maker and Monarch of all men: who is his Superiour? To whom ſhall he give account? Who ſhall expoſtulate with him for Injuſtice? Or for fear of whom ſhould he warp? He can ceaſe to be, as ſoon as leave to be juſt. The Apoſtle improves his very reaſon, to demonſtrate the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.5,6. <hi>Is God unrighteous who taketh vengeance; God forbid; How ſhall God judge the World?</hi> It being an Office excluſively belonging to him, by reaſon of his indep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ual Juſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>He ſhall judge the World;</hi> that's a reciev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Principle; from whence he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:137265:71"/> that therefore God cannot do unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.20. 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 1.6.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we come to clear this Doctrine from <hi>Objections;</hi> for this Bright and Shining Truth is very Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to ſore Eyes; as the moſt Evangelical Diſcoveries are not without Fierce Oppoſitions. It is the Devils work to Impriſon all Truth, but the nobler and more pretious Truths, muſt expect to be put in the loweſt and darkeſt Dungeon; as here now the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God; the Flower and Crown of Heaven; how would he eclipſe this Fair Sun! And,</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>1. It is Objected,</label> 
                     <hi>That God did Ordain ſome of his Creatures to Puniſhment and Damnation, without Fault and Deſert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Divine Purpoſes are very unſearcheable, they lye wrapt up in everlaſting Darkneſs and are covered in a deep Abyſs, none can Fathome the Bottom. Yet to this Objector, I ſay, it is moſt falſe: and a Calumny uſually caſt upon the Doctrine of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt nation;</hi> and which the Rhetorick of our Adverſaries, is wont to blow
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:137265:72"/> up to the higheſt pitch of Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion even to the Impeaching of Gods Juſtice which is moſt Blaſphemous. But to the Anſwer,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God Created man for his own Glory, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimately;</hi> and if any Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry through their own Default, (as it will be found they do,) God will be glorified in them as well as in others. The Howlings of them which periſh, ſhall render forth his Praiſe, as well as the <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> of them that are Saved. They both ſing unto the Glorious Attributes of the Bleſſed Trinity an everlaſting <hi>Canticle.</hi> On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this great Conſort of the Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Creation, the deſignedly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring Voices are as differing as the Condition of the reſpective Singers. Hell's Darkneſs ſhall as well contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to Gods Glory, as Heavens e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Splendours. As ſhadows Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly placed, do no leſs praiſe the Painter, than do the livelier and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Colours.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In Ordaining, he is to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as a Lord, not as a Judge. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and Reprobation being Acts of Power and Prerogative: ſo that in theſe the matter of Right and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:137265:72"/> Wrong are not concerned. Gods Volitions and Decrees are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on any temporal Objects, as Motives thereunto; but determine without any Reſpect to any Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Creature; and what Injuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice can be therein? The clay ſhould not diſpute with the Potter. None ſhould argue againſt Divine Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative. <hi>Ratio quoſdam elegit &amp; quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam reprobat, non habet rationem niſi Divinam Voluntatem.</hi> Aqu. 1 part 4. 23. Art 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He doth puniſh none without fault, nor condemn any without De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. God who is pure Juſtice, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth no prejudice upon the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but as provoked by ſome Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal miſcarriage; though it be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the Reprobate ſhall dye, yet <hi>Sin,</hi> not the <hi>Decree</hi> is the cauſe of Death. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>By Sin Death entred into the World.</hi> To crown or to damn is an Act of judiciary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and proceeds according to the Tenour of the Revealed Goſpel. The Eternal Decree of the Damnation of the very <hi>Devils,</hi> was never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to be Executed otherways than for their own Miſdeeds.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:137265:73"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>2. It is objected,</label> 
                     <hi>The Author of Sin cannot be juſt.</hi> Ergo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Innocency it ſelf cannot be protected from Imputations; though the Reproach will ſtick no faſter, than a Bur that is caſt againſt a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal; fot it will eaſily appear, that God is neither <hi>Autho</hi> or <hi>Actor Pec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cati:</hi> He makes Sin no more than the Sun makes the Night. Though <hi>Bellarmin</hi> labour to impoſe this Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy on <hi>Calvin, Beza,</hi> and <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius,</hi> as their opinions; Yet the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and ſome of his own So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, clear him, as ſaying, 1. That he willeth Sin <hi>permiſſively,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it could not be, <hi>Miro &amp; in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili modo non fit praeter ejus volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quod etiam fit contra ejus volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem; Quia non fieret niſi ſinerit, nec utique nolens ſinit, ſed volens: As Aug. Enchirid.</hi> And again, <hi>Non ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerit bonus fieri male, niſi Omnipotens etiam de malo poſſet facere bonum.</hi> Ibid. The Lord thought it better to do good with evil, than not to permit it: And it is acknowledged, that Sin the worſt thing that is, but the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of Sin is not Evil; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaith <hi>Aug.</hi> God would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:137265:73"/>
                  <p n="2">2. God concurs <hi>ad Actum &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminationem voluntatis in particulari, non ad obliquitatem Actus.</hi> God doth concur to the Action and ſuſtains the Agent; For 'tis ſain, <hi>by him all things conſiſt.</hi> Coloſſ. 1.17. and <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>In him we live and move,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we are acted by him So that the bare Action is good and the fault wholly remains with the Creature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Obj.</label> 
                     <hi>But he that doth not hinder Sin when he may, is guilty.</hi> So a wicked <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rcian</hi> asketh, why the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d who foreſaw the event, did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Eve</hi> and the Devil to confer, and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e were able, why did he not hinder Sin to be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Thus men preſuming upon certain A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioms of Crooked and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted Reaſon, will und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtake to paſs Sentence upon God. The Rule will hold true in Reſpect of men, <hi>qui non vetat peccare, cum poſſit, jubet;</hi> but not in Reſpect of God, who is bound to no Law; neither did he ſuffer Sin unreproved or unpuniſhed. <hi>Proſper and Hilarius</hi> both, with <hi>Auſtin,</hi> make anſwer to this Queſtion, <hi>why God did
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:137265:74"/> not hinder Sin?</hi> the cauſe may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, it cannot be unjuſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>3. It is Objected;</label> 
                     <hi>God doth Diſtribute unequally, evil things to good men and good things to evil men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> This is a bad and common Charge. The ſeeming Diſregard and Inequality of Providence, hath cauſed ſome to charge God fooliſhly. Among Heathens of old, we find <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> an able Aſſertor of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, ſuch as he knew; when finally vanquiſhed by <hi>Antonius</hi> and ſaw ſuch bad Succeſs in ſo good a Cauſe, as he thought his to be, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed all Vertue and derided all Endeavours of living well, as vain and bootleſs. And <hi>Pompey</hi> when diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> blamed Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as if there were a Miſt over it. But both blamed the Sun, becauſe of their own ſore eyes. And theſe well-tempered Heathens were not alone, but men of other make have ſtumbled at the ſame Stone. It was <hi>Davids</hi> Caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2.3. <hi>As for me, my Step were almoſt gone, my Feet had well nigh ſlipt, for I was envious at the Fooliſh</hi> &amp;c. and the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, Chap.</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:137265:74"/> 12.1. <hi>Why doth the way of the Wicked proſper &amp;c.</hi> Which is as though he had ſaid, Why ſhall ſuch Weeds as Cumber the Ground be watered ſo plentifully and grow ſo exceedingly, when good Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n is ſo thin and Lean? Why ſhall the Lyon and Raven, thoſe unclean Creatures, be ſpared, when the innocent Lamb and Dove are Sacrificed? The wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked flouriſh, like a Bay-tree, and enjoy a Conſtant Spring and Summer, though without Fruit, when the Saints, like good Apple-trees, have their Autumn and Winter? This hath touched good men to the quick; ſore eyes could not behold the glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ious Sun-ſhine of wicked mens Proſperity, without much pain. But however God is juſt. Therefore to anſwer the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, I ſay, he that doth ſo finally, is unjuſt. <hi>Differt nunc D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us, non De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminat;</hi> God will have men to be known. Some ſerve him only for a Livery; dayes of Adverſity are Gods fans or Furnace; <hi>non Approbat facta Impiorum;</hi> he approves not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly in their wayes; though at Gods Connivance and preſent Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of their Helliſh Practices, they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:137265:75"/> make damnable Inferences of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving them. <hi>Becauſe they have no Changes, they fear not God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 4.</label> 
                     <hi>Suppoſe two perſons for natural Diſpoſition Equal, the one is taken and effectually called, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left; is not here Reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Here is more bubling up of Carnal Reaſon againſt Divine Diſpenſation: the ſame Anſwer occurs here for Subſtance, as to the former.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Certain it is that theſe two Terms, <hi>Righteous Judgement,</hi> and <hi>Accepting of Perſons,</hi> are differently Oppoſite. But here is no <hi>reſpect of Perſons:</hi> the Working of God, on which the Object is founded, is <hi>actus Pote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tiae Liberae, potius quam Juſtitiae,</hi> an act of free Power, rather than of Juſtice. And Divines have received it for a Principle, That <hi>Accepting of Perſons,</hi> is not found <hi>in Gratuitis,</hi> in Acts of Bounty, wherein the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor is at Liberty to diſpoſe of his free Gift, as pleaſeth himſelf; but <hi>in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis,</hi> in Acts of Juſtice and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, wherein lieth an Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on him that Diſtributeth, to give
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:137265:75"/> every man his due. Hereon they Conclude, that in Divine Choice, God is no Debtor to any of his Creatures, but Acteth therein, not as a Judge, but as a Soveraign Lord and Liberal Benefactor, chooſing ſome, and paſſing by others; as without Injuſtice or Wrong to any, ſo without ſhew of accepting of Perſons, <hi>Auguſtin</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting this Queſtion largly againſt the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lagians,</hi> brings in the Inſtance of a man that hath two Debtors, of whom he forgives one, and requires full Payment of the other; if any demand the Reaſon, he anſwereth, <hi>It is my Will:</hi> and ſo God giveth Effectual Grace to one and not to another, this is his <hi>Free Power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is juſt, becauſe according to his Will and Wiſdom. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Therefore hath he Mercy on whom he will,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore not injuſt, becauſe hidden to us. If this do not ſatisfie, I ſhall refer ſuch to conſider what one of our Antient Writers did to their Forefathers; <hi>Heron in Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. ad C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſiphontem,</hi> viz. The Apoſtle, ſaith he, having diſcourſed of this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, acknowledgeth their depths, and adoreth the Wiſdom of God in them,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:137265:76"/> 
                     <hi>Dignare &amp; tu iſta neſcire; concede Deo potentiam ſui; nequaquam te indiget Defenſore:</hi> Be thou alſo willing to be ignorant of ſuch things. Leave God to himſelf in mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lling of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Diſpenſations; he will be ſure to do it ſo, as not to ſtand in need of any Apology or Defence from thee!</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>4. Objected it is,</label> 
                     <hi>What Juſtice is it in God, to command a man by his Word, the perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ce of which cannot be done by him, without the inward help of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rit, and yet in the mean whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, deny that help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the Spirit to him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Fair words; but a trick whereby men of towring Thoughts labour to bring the Royal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Converting Grace, into the hands of ſinful Clay, and ſo derogate f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om the honour of him who is the Former of all things. But muſt it needs be a blemiſh to Gods Honour and a ſtain to his Juſtice, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand man to perform his Duty, though he have no ſtrength to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it? Once he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ſtrength, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd hath loſt it; but G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d hath not loſt his Right to command, though man
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:137265:76"/> hath loſt his Ability to obey. A Drunken Servant is not diſobliged to ſerve; nor a broken Merchant to pay his Creditors. It is a Right Rule to be obſerved in unknitting this Knot; <hi>Mandata Dei, non ſunt Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura noſtrerum virium, ſed Regula Officii &amp; materia praecum;</hi> as Molinus <hi>Contr. Amyrald.</hi> Precepts and Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ordinarily ſignifie the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving Will of the Commander, and his Duty to whom they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; although ſometime the Duty of the Hearer, rather than the Will of the Speaker, be declared by them: They ſhew us what we ought to do, not what we can; they aſſure us what God will do when he pleaſeth, not what he is bound to do, Grace is free. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ither can any Creature chall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>l Grace at Gods hands, as a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Debt, ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her to his Nature or his Labour; however ſome ſawcil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>k of God, as if he we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to do this or that, to giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his or the other Grace, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> produ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de himſelf a Debto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is the zeal of <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r L <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rd. Lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Sent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct.</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:137265:77"/> 43. againſt ſuch men; <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi videtur, hoc verbum</hi> [Debet] <hi>venenum habet, — nec Deo proprium competit, quia non eſt debitor nobis, niſi forte expromiſſo.</hi> To me, ſaith he, this word <hi>[he ought]</hi> or, he is <hi>bound,</hi> ſeems to have much poiſon in it, and cannot properly belong to God, who is no Debtor to us, ſave only in thoſe caſes, wherein he hath paſſed ſome free Promiſe. And I am ſure, our Saviour tells his Diſciples plainly, <hi>It is given to you to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven, to others it is not given,</hi> Math. 13.11. And the Houſholder in the Parable, ſtops the Mouths of thoſe Murmurers that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pined, as expecting more from him than it was his pleaſure to give, with the ſole conſideration of its being his Will ſo to have it, <hi>Friend I do thee no wrong,</hi> &amp;c. Math. 20.10,13. <hi>Dei judicia nemo plene comprehendit, nemo juſte reprehendit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>5. It is Objected,</label> 
                     <hi>God commanded</hi> Abraham <hi>to kill his Son.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> 1. He may do that, which he hath forbid us to do; as appears out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.16. Compared with 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.6. For although by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:137265:77"/> Law, Magiſtrates be forbidden to put Children to Death for their Parents Sins; yet God, who is the Author of Life and Death, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to himſelf a Liberty of ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whenſoever it ſhall ſo pleaſe him, by Reaſon of his ſupream Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over all; and therefore for him to Inflict inferiour temporal Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhments in that caſe, cannot but be accounted juſt; and the rather, if we Conſider, that Children may be accounted part of their Parents; for as a mans Wife is himſelf divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo his Children are himſelf Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Gods command to <hi>Abraham</hi> was but <hi>Manda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um Explorationis,</hi> not <hi>Seductionis,</hi> a Command of Tryal, not of Seduction. God is ſaid to <hi>Tempt,</hi> when he puts us upon the Trial of our Faith and Obedience, that he may do us good in the latter end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.26. but to <hi>Seduce</hi> he cannot be ſaid to do. The Author of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Good, cannot be the Author of Sin: as before is Noted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object.</label> 
                     <hi>Did he not bid</hi> Shimei <hi>to curſe</hi> David!</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> True; as a Puniſhment on
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:137265:78"/> 
                     <hi>David;</hi> but it was a Sin in <hi>Shimei:</hi> his ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was to drive <hi>David</hi> to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, but God directed it to Humble him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>6. It is Objected;</label> 
                     <hi>How it could ſtand with Justice in God to ſet forth his Innocent Son to ſuffer?</hi> From this the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cinian</hi> party cry out againſt us, as if God were charged with Tyranny, in laying the Puniſhment of Offendors on our Innocent Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; which alſo drew from <hi>Brentius</hi> a <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eran,</hi> thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſphemy, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Pater in cruce Tyrannus egit erga Filium,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> To which I anſwer, 1. It was with his Will, which is the Rule of Juſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſi quia Volitum, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mvis non t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>um qua V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>litum, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nus S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntia dictatum. Dei V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>tat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s eſt ſemper licet non C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> This was concluded on as the moſt Cong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nous and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient mean to man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>feſt Mercy and Juſtice; an exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llent Temperament ſo that one doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the o her. God will not let Sin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, therefore he prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>m to be Sacrific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d for <hi>Iſaac;</hi> a Mediatour to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:137265:78"/> come between us and Wrath. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Reaſon do moſt gainſay this Myſtery, we muſt ſay, <hi>Taceat ista Mulier in Eccleſia;</hi> Let this woman hold her Peace in the Church. Hear what the word ſaith, and believe; <hi>Chriſt ſuffered that God might be juſt;</hi> Rom. 3.26. If this will not Satisfie, I anſwer farther.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt may be conſidered two wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> as he is in himſelf a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body, without any Relation to us; and ſo no action of his concerned us, nor any of ours concerned him; or as he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part of a Body Myſtical; in which Conſideration, his Actions and ours concern us jointly: for if the hand be Wounded, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ad will ſay, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me. Thus we read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26. <hi>If one M mber ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r, all the Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffer with it.</hi> For in this R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtands to his People by Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> graciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Covenant m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ween God the Father and Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Son, and ſecretly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ween them, be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>re the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion of the World. From which Union between Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers is produ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>word w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Divines call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a mutual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:137265:79"/> of Properties; which work extends it ſelf ſo far, as that the Perfections and Excellencies which are Originally peculiar to the Perſon of Chriſt, are Communicated unto, and truely affirmed of holy men; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. and ſo the Infirmities, yea the Sins of his Members, are Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated unto and Affirmed of, and Imputed to Chriſt. <hi>He was made Sin for us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. though in the ſame Breath, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He knew no Sin;</hi> both which are moſt true; becauſe our Sins are his Sins, by Reaſon of this Union: as the Debt of the Principal is alſo the Debt of the Surety. In which Senſe, Chriſt is ſaid to be ſlain from before the <hi>Foundation of the World, Revel.</hi> 13.8. even before he was Incarnat; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of <hi>Abel,</hi> who was his Member and Type. Chriſt ſuffered for the Sins of his People, which are his Sins in that himſelf and Members are one; and no Injuſtice doth appear as to this Miniſtration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>7. It is objected;</label> 
                     <hi>Good men are ſwept away in common judgments, as the wicked are.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Outward things come alike
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:137265:79"/> to all. So <hi>Solomon;</hi> to Saints as well as Sinners. What they ſay of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that <hi>Non datur purum elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> there is no pure, unmixt Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that is ſtrained and ſublimated and as it were framed into ſuch an Harmony, that it hath always an healthful Predominancy, but mixt, and whereby Diſeaſes break in; the like may be ſaid of Divine Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations towards the beſt of people; there is a mixture in them; the Saints are not ever ſingled out as Objects of ſenſible Mercies. Their Sun oftentimes ſets in a Cloud; their Ship in common Tempeſts is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed; But,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is not ſo always. <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> ſhall be ſtanding Witneſſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo long as the World ſhall ſtand. They were ſtanding Monuments of Gods Preſervation, in the then Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins of the Worlds Deſolation. Though an Houſholder ſpend and ſell the greateſt part of the Harveſt Crop, yet he will be ſure to preſerve a little Seed-Corn, to ſow his ground for a new Crop. Though <hi>Sodom</hi> be utterly deſtroyed by Fire, yet <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is as a <hi>Brand pluckt out of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:137265:80"/> Fire.</hi> God maketh a light account of a whole City full of Sinners; he takes away the ungodly of the earth like droſs, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.119. which is put into the Fire to be conſumed. His own people ſhall be preſerved. Though he make a full end of all Nations, yet he will not make a full end of his people, but correct them in meaſure. He will have <hi>ſome</hi> to be Monuments of his Mercy, for in the midſt of Judgments he will beloved, as well as feared in his ſmiles.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Never as the wicked are; though in Afflictions, and National Calamities eſpecially, God oftentimes ſeems to make no diſtinction between the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his Compaſſion and Fury, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcriminately involving them in the ſame deſtiny; yet his <hi>Intention</hi> makes a vaſt difference, where his <hi>infliction</hi> ſeems to make none: As when on the ſame teſt, and with the ſelf-ſame Fire, Chymiſts do urge the Gold as well as the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anded Lead; but withal foreknowing and deſigning ſuch a diſparity in the Events, as to conſume the ignoble Minerals, or blow them off into Droſs and Fumes, and make the Gold more pure and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:137265:80"/> full of Luſtre. Even ſo doth God in his ſevere Diſpenſations towards his people in common with the wicked; to the one they are deſtructive, to the other Purgative, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.9. <hi>By this ſhall the Iniquity if Jacob be purged,</hi> &amp;c. When the evil of Affliction over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes a wicked man, it is to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Soul; when it comes to a godly man, it comes only to take away his Sin. A rotten cloath if it be ſcour'd and rub'd, it breaks and tears; but a piece of Braſs well ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, will ſhine the brighter; Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on wicked mens falſe hearts, break them, but the ſame on good men, amend and better them.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee the Objections are but as oppoſing the ſhadow to the light, and a lye to truth; and how they who go about to put out the truth of God, by ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſing, make it burn the brighter. Neither indeed was it ever poſſible for the enemies of <hi>Gods Righteouſneſs</hi> by all their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to compaſs their Deſign; all the vapours of mens Brains, are not able to cloud ſo bright a Sun. The uſe of all follows.</p>
                  <p>And, 1. This Doctrine, like a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:137265:81"/> direful Comet which carries with it Blood and deſtruction, ſpeaks dread and terrour, and it hath a double a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. On the whole Land in general, and ſo it ſadly threatens, Conſidering,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> What is done by us. Sinful we are to aſtoniſhment: that of the Prophet may be applied to us, <hi>Hear O Heaven, and Hearken O Earth, I have brought up Children, and they have Rebelled againſt me!</hi> Secure we are, fearing no evil, ſetting light by the means, vapouring out the good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of a pleaſant Land, in a <hi>vain Converſation.</hi> Our Calm and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Goſpel dayes have brought forth in us Spiders and Caterpillars, and the like Vermine, even Pride, Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, Prophaneneſs, Atheiſm, Spirits averſe to the power of Godlineſs, and a ſound Reformation; Witneſs that general Apoſtacy to Formality, Will-worſhip, and ſtrange Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Popery, and ſuch-like innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and which is a great aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſhew our inexcuſableneſs, God hath been correcting us, to amend us, but we have been the more vile and ſinful. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.1. <hi>When I would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:137265:81"/> have Healed Iſrael, then the Iniquity of Ephraim was diſcovered,</hi> &amp;c. Zeal is exceedingly decayed, the word ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and Religion meets with much ſnarling and oppoſition every where. How impudent is Sin grown? God looked for purging of the Land, and behold it is more defiled. When the Pot boyleth the Scum is diſcover'd. Baths bring forth Corruption (if it be in the Body) into the Skin: God hath been reforming the Land; and our Wickedneſs appears the more. Time was when Sin began to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to creep into Corners, to be out of Faſhion, but now it is grown brazen faced, walks in the open Streets, ſeems to be in requeſt more than ever. Thus our Sins <hi>teſtify a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us,</hi> are grown up to Heaven, and darken the Sun, put out the Moon, ſeal up the Conſtellations, to intercept the paſſage of Prayer thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to ſtop the influences of the light of Heaven from deſcending hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or to knock at the Gate, to ſollicite for vengeance upon us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> what the Lord hath done to others ſo offending; even took away his Glory, and gave them up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:137265:82"/> the Enemies hands; bringing them into a Spiritual <hi>Egypt:</hi> Witneſs the famous <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Tyranny. There was a time when the Vineyard, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.4. ſhould have afforded <hi>red Wine,</hi> and then it might have expected Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every moment, and Continued Preſervation, but this Vineyard De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating, inſtead of <hi>Red Wine,</hi> it brought forth <hi>Wild Grapes;</hi> and then inſtead of keeping, the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to take away the Hedge, and pull down the Walls thereof: inſtead of Preſerving it from hurt, to let it be eaten up, broken down, inſtead of Watering, to command the Clouds to yield it no Rain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſidering, what he hath done amongſt us; how he goeth on by Degrees. <hi>God is juſt,</hi> and when the Number is up, the rod will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall; when the Corn is ripe, the Sickle is prepared. Though he break not the Candleſtick, he may, for ought we know, remove it, and not leave ſo much as any quality, title or Property of a Church; he may deal with us, as he did with <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and who knows but that the Lord
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:137265:82"/> hath ſaid of us in this Nation, as he did of the old Church of the <hi>Jews, Deut.</hi> 32.32,33. <hi>Their Vine is the Vine of Sodom,</hi> &amp;c. Sure I am, he hath already begun to cut the Vine, till it bleed; and if Repentance ſteps not in to turn away Wrath, he may be provoked to ſay to <hi>England</hi> as he once did to <hi>Paleſtina, Jer.</hi> 2.21. <hi>I Planted thee a noble Vine, wholly a right ſeed; how then art thou turned a degenerate Plant of a ſtrange Vine unto me?</hi> And not only loan us out, but ſet us to whole-ſale; and make the Kingdom an Holocauſt to his juſt Indignation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. On the prophane and ungodly in ſpecial. This Doctrine is to them an Arrow ſent from Heaven, Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered with Wrath and headed with Ruine. It is a hand from Heaven, an Alarm from thence. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> what the Lord hath threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19,20. <hi>The Lord will not ſpare that man, he ſhall not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape.</hi> Do not think the Lord to be a God of Clou ts, one, that however he ſpeak heavy words, yet will not do as he ſaith; ſay not with them in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:137265:83"/> 
                     <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.13. Words are but <hi>Wind;</hi> and with them in the Goſpel, <hi>God forbid!</hi> Do not fancy to your ſelves a God made up wholly of Mercy, and ſo act arbitrarily, living as you pleaſe: for verily you will find, he hath blows as well as words, and that the cry of Sin, will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be followed with the eccho of Wrath. Clouds contains the ſhowers of Rain that fall on the earth, and ſo do Threatnings contain the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that purſue Sinners. As in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> you never read that the Heavens opened, but ſome great matter followed; ſo it is here. <hi>Hath the Lord ſpoken, and ſhall he not do it?</hi> Verily, his word ſhall not paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way unfulfilled!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> what he hath done, to the <hi>Old World, Sodom, Achan, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab, Saul, Herod,</hi> and ſuch like Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againſt their own Souls. He hath made Arrows of all Wood, and vengeance of all Creatures to puniſh their Demerit, he hath fallen upon them more ſwift than Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, Eagles, or impetuous Storms. They are ſo many viſible Sermons, and ſpeak the determinations of God,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:137265:83"/> real Stories to be read by you, that you may not become Stories for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to read. <hi>Then ſhall he ſpeak to them in his Wrath,</hi> &amp;c. Behold theſe examples in a way of particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, as bringing Tidings of Ruine, and ſaying, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you Repent, you ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> As Judges uſe to hang up notorious Offendor in Chains, to be a terrour to all Spectators, ſo hath the Lord done with many obſtinate Sinners; he hath Thundred and Lightned over their rebellious heads, none of them were able to reſiſt his Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſidering what you have deſerved; even to be delivered up to a <hi>reprobate ſenſe,</hi> Rom. 1.28. to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a lye,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. to be <hi>turned into Hell,</hi> where your Horrour and Lamentations ſhould be the Muſick of Gods Juſtice, and the Heraulds of his Righteous Severity to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object.</label> 
                     <hi>But ſhall we be ſo dealt with?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> Yes, without Repentance and ſpeedy turning to God. It is but as he is juſt, he will find you out. The Rocks and Mountains ſhall not be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:137265:84"/> able to ſhelter you from the Wrath of him that ſits on the Throne. May the terrours of God prevail with you! O be importunate with the moſt High to cut the thred of your Wickedneſs, that you may not ſpin it out to a full Length. Put to your own ſtrength to break off the Match between you and Sin, and Sue out a Divorce; <hi>Break off thy Sins by Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſaith <hi>Daniel</hi> to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi> Cut this <hi>Gordian</hi> Knot. If you have any Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity of Spirit, any ſparks of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, conſider your latter end; now begin to found a retreat, fold up your Enſigns; It is not too late, the door of Grace is yet open. Proteſt not to perſevere in Miſchief, like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils. There are none but enraged Spirits, that will be healed by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of their own ill, and bury themſelves in their ruin. Wiſe men alwayes make a Medicine for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of others Folly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</label> This Doctrine ſounds moſt incomparable Comfort to all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God, and called unto Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Conſidering,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> what he hath promiſed; <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 28.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.22,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:137265:84"/> 25,26. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. &amp;c. Theſe are a Noſegay of ſweet Flowers taken out of the Scripture-garden; make uſe of them; Let your Meditation, like the Bee, ſuck the ſweetneſs of them. They'le prove as Bezar-ſtone to keep you from fainting under your Sins and Sorrows. Get more acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with them, O Ye Sons of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption. Be not like unskilfull La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidaries, little valuing the worth of ſuch Orient Pearls, which are the Riches and the only Treaſure of the Heirs of Glory, on this fide Heaven. Suck at theſe Breaſts; take Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage from thoſe Heavenly Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſidering what he hath done. He hath been Mindfull of his Covenant, neither will he forget. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. <hi>God is not unrighteous to forget your work and labour of Love, which you have ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wed towards his Name, in that ye have ministred to the Saints, and do miniſter.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6,7,8.</p>
                  <p>You have three ſure Foundations to build upon.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You have his Attributes of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and Truth. Whatever he hath pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſed, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll be performed. His
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:137265:85"/> promiſe may lye a long time, as Seed, under ground, but it is all the while a Ripening. Shall not God be true? If not, who ſhall? He will be ſo far from coming ſhort of his word, that he will better it. He often ſhoots be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Mark of his Promiſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhort of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His immutable purpoſe; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>The Foundation of God ſtandeth ſure,</hi> &amp;c. and, <hi>The Gifts and calling of God are without Repentance.</hi> It cannot be ſaid of God, as it is of man, that though his Goodneſs be ſweet, yet it is ſhort, though he can do enough for us, yet his mind may change or his Promiſe be broken; No, as he is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral in all his expreſſions, ſo he is unchangeable in his intentions of your good. Where he loves, he loves ever.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. You have his Seal and Earneſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. called the <hi>firſt Fruits</hi> of the Spirit, Rom. 8.23. as <hi>Iſraels</hi> Grapes in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> were the <hi>first Fruits</hi> of <hi>Canaan;</hi> what pledge can be more certain than the <hi>Earneſt of the Spirit: Epheſ.</hi> 1.14. If this Foundation fail, you may well ſay with the Prophet <hi>David,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:137265:85"/> What ſhall the Righteous do?</hi> But ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall the huge Rock be broken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bits, and thrown as Pebbles and Cockle-ſhells upon the Shoar, by the violence of Waves; ſooner ſhall the Mountains that God hath ſet faſt by his ſtrength, be overturned by the breath of Tempeſtuous Winds, than the Promiſes which are founded upon the immutable Power of God and his never failing Goodneſs, be in the leaſt Iota made void and of none effect.</p>
                  <p>Now as ſome kind of Artificers, after long poring on a piece of black work, finding a dimneſs in their eyes, are wont to take an Emerald, or ſome other green thing, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure whereof they may be refreſhed, and their Spirits cheered; thus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers when dulled and puzzled with the conſideration of ſad, ſtrange and contrariant Events in the World, may for their ſpiritual Relief, make uſe of this Cordial, theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions laid before them, their luſtre will be exceeding cheering to the eye of Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3.</label> Hence is offered ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thing of <hi>inſtruction;</hi> and that diverſly:</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:137265:86"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> In matters of <hi>Contentation</hi> and ſubmiſſion to all his Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Providence is the beſt <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld</hi> to Marſhal us, and we ought to fit down content, without murmuring at Gods diſpoſing Juſtice. Thus <hi>Job</hi> practiſed; <hi>The Lord giveth and the Lord taketh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, when his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were Murthered before him, and his own eyes afterward bored out, uttered this Speech, <hi>Juſtus es Domine &amp; Recta judicia tua:</hi> Thou art Righteous O Lord in all thy ways. That we are ſpared it is his Mercy; that we are puniſhed, cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. However things go in the World, could we have hard thoughts of Sin, all our thoughts of Gods dealings with us, would be moſt honourable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> in matter of <hi>Imitation;</hi> and ſo,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> in executing Juſtice. Here's a Copy for them to write after. See the Rule, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Judge R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ghteous Judgment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween every man and his Brother.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is the Soul of Judgment. An un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Judge, is a Soleciſm, a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. God will do Juſtice upon men,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:137265:86"/> be they what they will be; ſo muſt Magiſtrates execute Juſtice imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. They muſt be the Law enliven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they muſt be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaks, Living Images of God; who when he is in the greatneſs of his Power, is <hi>moſt juſt.</hi> Though he could check all the world that ſpeak againſt him, yet he will do <hi>righteous things, Pſalm</hi> 48.10. <hi>Thy Right Hand is full of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Gods Right Hand is an embelm of of his ſtrength, and it is <hi>full of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Thus ſhould men be exalted to higheſt place of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they ſhould be <hi>full of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi> It is not enough that Juſtice be in the Laws, but it muſt be in the Judges too, elſe no honour, no ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>curity of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Juſtice in the Law, is like Gold in the Mine, which while it is there only, doth no man good; but when in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, it is like Gold coined, for Uſe and Honour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For <hi>Miniſters,</hi> to declare his Righteouſneſs, and not to fear for any Amazement; Concealing it before great men, covering thoſe Sins with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:137265:87"/> Silence which they know them guilty of. <hi>Greatneſs</hi> muſt not be a <hi>Buff-coat</hi> to any mans Wickedneſs. We know Phyſitians and Chyrurgeons (and ſo Miniſters) are ſometimes allowed to be Cruel. The Lapping up of the Pills of Reproof, in much Pap and Sugar, by allaying the bitterneſs, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Operation is fruſtrated. Miniſters muſt not Complement Souls into Hell. They muſt not feaſt mens ears, but Wound their Hearts; not lick the ſores of great ones, and Bite the Sores of poor ones. This is not juſt. <hi>Nathan</hi> did not ſo; nor <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt before <hi>Herod,</hi> nor <hi>Paul</hi> before <hi>Felix;</hi> nor <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> before <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> nor <hi>Ambroſe</hi> under <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius;</hi> nor <hi>Bernard</hi> it ſeems by his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to <hi>Eugenius.</hi> Let no Siniſter End divert you from the Publication of Gods Juſtice. It is a work of your Place and Office. It was the work of Chriſt, of his Apoſtles and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in all ages. O, manifeſt ſome Sparklings of this <hi>Diviner</hi> Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo like that which appeared in thoſe Tranſcendants among Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Lo I am with you!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. For <hi>People</hi> in all their earthly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:137265:87"/> Tranſactions. As one wrote to <hi>Egi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> Abbot of <hi>Norinburg,</hi> concerning the 119. Pſal. <hi>Haec non ſunt Verba ſolum Legenda ſed Vivenda;</hi> ſo may I ſpeak here to you; theſe things are not ſpoken and Written to be heard or read only, but to be lived. <hi>This, the Grace of God which hath appeared to all men, teacheth you.</hi> A Duty as neceſſary to Salvation, as that which immediately refers to God himſelf. <hi>Moſes</hi> came out of the Mount with both Tables in his Hands; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond as well as the firſt. They muſt go both together; one ſtone in a Mill will do but little good. A Bird cannot Fly with one Wing. Many pleaſe themſelves with a Single Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God in the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Law, having little Regard of the ſecond towards man; this Argues little Sincerity. You muſt give God and men their due: Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4</label> And laſtly, The Uſe is for <hi>Reformation</hi> and Preparation to meet the Lord, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. The Lord is juſt and the Judgment day is at Hand. <hi>Currat ergo Paenitentia, ne praecurrat Sententia,</hi> ſaith one. <hi>Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:137265:88"/> Preces et Lachrymas Cordis Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatos,</hi> ſaith another. Haſte, haſte to meet the Lord with Entreaties of Peace. By hearkning to his Word, believing and doing it; by Humbling your ſelves under his Rods, or at the Report of his Judgments. And to this end,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Caſt away your Sins, every man his Idols. Come out of the crooked Paths of Pride, Hypocriſy, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Barrenneſs and whatever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Godlineſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Give your ſelves to Faſting and Prayer, and Mourning, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12,13,17. Perhaps you may find Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Who knoweth but that the Lord may Return and leave a Bleſſing behind him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Put on Chriſt, and take him in your Arms. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.1,2,3. <hi>Gather your ſelves together, yea, gather together, O na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not deſired: Before the decree come forth, before the day of the Lords Anger come upon you.</hi> Rom. 13.12,13. <hi>The day is far ſpent, the night is at hand: Let us therefore cast off the Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and put on the Armour of Light. Let us walk honeſtly as in the day; not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in
<pb facs="tcp:137265:88"/> Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and Envying. But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> — This is the Garment with which you may come boldly before the Lord.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
